
=== PAGE 1 ===
2007 SECTION V 	ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M
ARTICLE 23
ULTRASONIC STANDARDS
SPECIFICATION FOR ULTRASONIC
EXAMINATION OF HEAVY
STEEL FORGINGS
SA-388/SA-388M
(Identical with ASTM Specification A 388 /A 388M-04)
1. 	Scope
1.1 	This practice covers the examination procedures
for the contact, pulse-echo ultrasonic examination of heavy
steel forgings by the straight- and angle-beam techniques.
The straight-beam techniques include utilization of the
DGS (Distance Gain Size) method. See Appendix X3.
1.2 	This practice is to be used whenever the inquiry,
contract, order, or specification states that forgings are to
be subject to ultrasonic examination in accordance with
Practice A 388/A 388M.
1.3 	The values stated in either inch-pound or SI units
are to be regarded as the standard. Within the text, the SI
units are shown in brackets. The values stated in each
system are not exact equivalents; therefore, each system
must be used independently of the other. Combining values
from the two systems may result in nonconformance with
the specification.
1.4 This specification and the applicable material speci-
fications are expressed in both inch-pound units and SI
units. However, unless the order specifies the applicable
“M” specification designation (SI units), the material shall
be furnished to inch-pound units.
1.5 	This standard does not purport to address all of
the safety concerns, if any, associated with its use. It is
the responsibility of the user of this standard to establish
appropriate safety and health practices and determine the
applicability of regulatory limitations prior to use.
351
2. 	Referenced Documents
2.1 ASTM Standards:
A 469 Specification for Vacuum-Treated Steel Forgings
for Generator Rotors
A 745/A 745M Practice for Ultrasonic Examination of
Austenitic Steel Forgings
E 317 Practice for Evaluating Performance Characteristics
of Ultrasonic Pulse-Echo Examination Instruments and
Systems Without the Use of Electronic Measurement
Instruments
E 428 Practice for Fabrication and Control of Steel Refer-
ence Blocks Used in Ultrasonic Inspection
2.2 ANSI Standard:
B46.1 Surface Texture
2.3 Other Document:
Recommended Practice for Nondestructive Personnel
Qualification and Certification SNT-TC-1A, Supple-
ment C — Ultrasonic Testing
3. 	Ordering Information
3.1 	When this practice is to be applied to an inquiry,
contract, or order, the purchaser shall so state and shall
also furnish the following information:
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--```,``,`,,````,,`,,`,,,`,,,```-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 2 ===
ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M 	2007 SECTION V
3.1.1 Method of establishing the sensitivity in accor-
dance with 7.2.2 and 7.3.3 (Vee or rectangular notch),
3.1.1.1 	The diameter and test metal distance of
the flat-bottom hole and the material of the reference block
in accordance with 7.2.2.2,
3.1.2 Quality level for the entire forging or portions
thereof in accordance with 10.3, and
3.1.3 	Any options in accordance with 6.1, 6.2, and
7.1.11.
4. 	Apparatus
4.1 An ultrasonic, pulsed, reflection type of instrument
shall be used for this examination. The system shall have
a minimum capability for examining at frequencies from
1 to 5 MHz. On examining austenitic stainless forgings
the system shall have the capabilities for examining at
frequencies down to 0.4 MHz.
4.1.1 	The ultrasonic instrument shall provide linear
presentation (within 5%) for at least 75% of the screen
height (sweep line to top of screen). The 5% linearity
referred to is descriptive of the screen presentation of
amplitude. Instrument linearity shall be verified in accor-
dance with the intent of Practice E 317. Any set of blocks
processed in accordance with Practice E 317 or E 428 may
be used to establish the specified ± 5% instrument linearity.
4.1.2 The electronic apparatus shall contain an atten-
uator [accurate over its useful range to ± 10% (± 1 dB)
of the amplitude ratio] which will allow measurement of
indications beyond the linear range of the instrument.
4.2 Search Units having a transducer with a maximum
active area of 1 in. 2 [650 mm 2 ] with 3 / 4 in. [20 mm]
minimum to 11 / 8 in. [30 mm] maximum dimensions shall
be used for straight-beam scanning (see 7.2); and search
units equipped from 1 / 2 by 1 in. [13 by 25 mm] to 1 by
1 in. [25 by 25 mm] shall be used for angle-beam scanning
(see 7.3).
4.2.1 Transducers shall be utilized at their rated fre-
quencies.
4.2.2 Other search units may be used for evaluating
and pinpointing indications.
4.3 Couplants having good wetting characteristics such
as SAE No. 20 or No. 30 motor oil, glycerin, pine oil, or
water shall be used. Couplants may not be comparable
to one another and the same couplant shall be used for
calibration and examination.
4.4 Reference Blocks containing flat-bottom holes may
be used for calibration of equipment in accordance with
4.1.1 and may be used to establish recording levels for
straight-beam examination when so specified by the order
or contract.
352
4.5 DGS scales, matched to the ultrasonic test unit and
transducer to be utilized, may be used to establish recording
levels for straight-beam examination, when so specified
by the order or contract. The DGS scale range must be
selected to include the full thickness cross-section of the
forging to be examined. An example of a DGS overlay is
found in Appendix X3.
5. 	Personnel Requirements
5.1 	Personnel performing the ultrasonic examinations
to this practice shall be qualified and certified in accordance
with a written procedure conforming to Recommended
Practice No. SNT-TC-1A or another national standard that
is acceptable to both the purchaser and the supplier.
6. 	Preparation of Forging for Ultrasonic
Examination
6.1 Unless otherwise specified in the order or contract,
the forging shall be machined to provide cylindrical sur-
faces for radial examination in the case of round forgings;
the ends of the forgings shall be machined perpendicular
to the axis of the forging for the axial examination. Faces
of disk and rectangular forgings shall be machined flat and
parallel to one another.
6.2 The surface roughness of exterior finishes shall not
exceed 250
in. [6
m] unless otherwise shown on the
forging drawing or stated in the order or the contract.
6.3 	The surfaces of the forging to be examined shall
be free of extraneous material such as loose scale, paint,
dirt, etc.
7. 	Procedure
7.1 General:
7.1.1 As far as practicable, subject the entire volume
of the forging to ultrasonic examination. Because of radii
at change of sections and other local configurations, it may
be impossible to examine some sections of a forging.
7.1.2 	Perform the ultrasonic examination after heat
treatment for mechanical properties (exclusive of stress-
relief treatments) but prior to drilling holes, cutting key-
ways, tapers, grooves, or machining sections to contour.
If the configuration of the forging required for the treatment
for mechanical properties prohibits a subsequent complete
examination of the forging, it shall be permissible to exam-
ine prior to treatment for mechanical properties. In such
cases, reexamine the forging ultrasonically as completely
as possible after heat treatment.
7.1.3 	To ensure complete coverage of the forging
volume, index the search unit with at least 15% overlap
with each pass.
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS

=== PAGE 3 ===
2007 SECTION V 	ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M
7.1.4 For manual scanning, do not exceed a scanning
rate of 6 in. /s [150 mm /s].
7.1.5 For automated scanning, adjust scanning speed
or instrument repetition rate, or both, to permit detection
of the smallest discontinuities referenced in the specifica-
tion and to allow the recording or signaling device to
function. At no time shall the scanning speed exceed the
speed at which an acceptable calibration was made.
7.1.6 If possible, scan all sections of forgings in two
perpendicular directions.
7.1.7 Scan disk forgings using a straight-beam tech-
nique from at least one flat face and radially from the
circumference, whenever practicable.
7.1.8 	Scan cylindrical sections and hollow forgings
radially using a straight beam. When practicable, also
examine the forging in the axial direction.
7.1.9 In addition, examine hollow forgings by angle-
beam technique from the outside diameter surface as
required in 7.3.1.
7.1.10 In rechecking or reevaluation by manufacturer
or purchaser use comparable equipment, search units, fre-
quency, and couplant.
7.1.11 	Forgings may be examined either stationary
or while rotating in a lathe or on rollers. If not specified
by the purchaser, either method may be used at the manu-
facturer’s option.
7.2 Straight-Beam Examination:
7.2.1 	For straight-beam examination use a nominal
2 1
⁄4 -MHz search unit whenever practicable; however,
1 MHz is the preferred frequency for coarse grained austen-
itic materials and long testing distances. In many instances
on examining coarse grained austenitic materials it may be
necessary to use a frequency of 0.4 MHz. Other frequencies
may be used if desirable for better resolution, penetrability,
or detectability of flaws.
7.2.2 	Establish the instrument sensitivity by either
the reflection, reference-block technique, or DGS method
(see Appendix X3 for an explanation of the DGS method).
7.2.2.1 Back-Reflection Technique (Back-Reflec-
tion Calibration Applicable to Forgings with Parallel
Entry and Back Surfaces) — With the attenuator set at an
appropriate level, for example 5 to 1 or 14 dB, adjust the
instrument controls to obtain a back reflection approxi-
mately 75% of the full-screen height from the opposite
side of the forging. Scan the forging at the maximum
amplification setting of the attenuator (attenuator set at
1 to 1). Carry out the evaluation of discontinuities with
the gain control set at the reference level. Recalibration is
required for significant changes in section thickness or
diameter.
353
NOTE 1 — High sensitivity levels are not usually employed when
inspecting austenitic steel forgings, due to attendant high level of “noise”
or “hash” caused by coarse grain structure.
7.2.2.2 Reference-Block Calibration — The test
surface roughness on the calibration standard shall be com-
parable to but no better than the item to be examined.
Adjust the instrument controls to obtain the required signal
amplitude from the flat-bottom hole in the specified refer-
ence block. Utilize the attenuator in order to set up on
amplitudes larger than the vertical linearity of the instru-
ment. In those cases, remove the attenuation prior to scan-
ning the forging.
NOTE 2 — When flat-surfaced reference block calibration is specified,
adjust the amplitude of indication from the reference block or blocks to
compensate for examination surface curvature (an example is given in
Appendix X1).
7.2.2.3 DGS Calibration — Prior to use, verify that
the DGS overlay matches the transducer size and fre-
quency. Accuracy of the overlay can be verified by refer-
ence blocks and procedures outlined in Practice E 317.
Overlays are to be serialized to match the ultrasonic trans-
ducer and pulse-echo testing system that they are to be
utilized with.
7.2.2.4 Choose the appropriate DGS scale for the
cross-sectional thickness of the forging to be examined.
Insert the overlay over the CRT screen, ensuring the DGS
scale baseline coincides with the sweep line of the CRT
screen. Place the probe on the forging, adjust the gain to
make the first backwall echo appear clearly on the CRT
screen. Using the Delay and Sweep control, shift the screen
pattern so that the leading edge of the initial pulse is on
zero of the DGS scale and the backwall echo is on the
DGS scale value corresponding to the thickness of the
forging. Adjust the gain so the forging backwall echo
matches the height of the DGS reference slope within
± 1 Db. Once adjusted, increase the gain by the Db shown
on the DGS scale for the reference slope. Instrument is
now calibrated and flaw sizes that can be reliably detected
can be directly read from the CRT screen. These flaw sizes
are the equivalent flat bottom reflector that can be used as
a reference point.
NOTE 3 — The above can be utilized on all solid forgings. Cylindrical
hollow forgings and drilled or bored forgings must be corrected to com-
pensate for attenuation due to the central hole (see Appendix X4).
7.2.3 Recalibration — Any change in the search unit,
couplant, instrument setting, or scanning speed from that
used for calibration shall require recalibration. Perform a
calibration check at least once every 8 h shift. When a loss
of 15% or greater in the gain level is indicated, reestablish
the required calibration and reexamine all of the material
examined in the preceding calibration period. When an
increase of 15% or greater in the gain level is indicated,
reevaluate all recorded indications.
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--```,``,`,,````,,`,,`,,,`,,,```-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 4 ===
ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M 	2007 SECTION V
7.2.4 During the examination of the forging, monitor
the back reflection for any significant reduction in ampli-
tude. Reduction in back-reflection amplitude may indicate
not only the presence of a discontinuity but also poor
coupling of the search unit with the surface of the forging,
nonparallel back-reflection surface, or local variations of
attenuation in the forging. Recheck any areas causing loss
of back reflection.
7.3 Angle-Beam Examination — Rings and Hollow
Forgings:
7.3.1 	Perform the examination from the circumfer-
ence of rings and hollow forgings that have an axial length
greater than 2 in. [50 mm] and an outside to inside diameter
ratio of less than 2.0 to 1.
7.3.2 	Use a 1 MHz, 45 deg angle-beam search unit
unless thickness, OD /ID ratio, or other geometric configu-
ration results in failure to achieve calibration. Other fre-
quencies may be used if desirable for better resolution,
penetrability, or detectability of flaws. For angle-beam
inspection of hollow forgings up to 2.0 to 1 ratio, provide
the transducer with a wedge or shoe that will result in the
beam mode and angle required by the size and shape of
the cross section under examination.
7.3.3 	Calibrate the instrument for the angle-beam
examination to obtain an indication amplitude of approxi-
mately 75% full-screen height from a rectangular or a 60
deg V-notch on inside diameter (ID) in the axial direction
and parallel to the axis of the forging. A separate calibration
standard may be used; however, it shall have the same
nominal composition, heat treatment, and thickness as the
forging it represents. The test surface finish on the calibra-
tion standard shall be comparable but no better than the
item to be examined. Where a group of identical forgings
is made, one of these forgings may be used as the separate
calibration standard. Cut the ID notch depth to 3% maxi-
mum of the thickness or 1 / 4 in. [6 mm], whichever is
smaller, and its length approximately 1 in. [25 mm]. Thick-
ness is defined as the thickness of the forging to be exam-
ined at the time of examination. At the same instrument
setting, obtain a reflection from a similar OD notch. Draw
a line through the peaks of the first reflections obtained
from the ID and OD notches. This shall be the amplitude
reference line. It is preferable to have the notches in excess
metal or test metal when possible. When the OD notch
cannot be detected when examining the OD surface, per-
form the examination when practicable (some IDs may be
too small to permit examination) as indicated above from
both the OD and ID surfaces. Utilize the ID notch when
inspecting from the OD, and the OD notch when inspecting
from the ID. Curve wedges or shoes may be used when
necessary and practicable.
7.3.4 Perform the examination by scanning over the
entire surface area circumferentially in both the clockwise
354
and counter-clockwise directions from the OD surface.
Examine forgings, which cannot be examined axially using
a straight beam, in both axial directions with an angle-
beam search unit. For axial scanning, use rectangular or
60 deg V-notches on the ID and OD for the calibration.
These notches shall be perpendicular to the axis of the
forging and the same dimensions as the axial notch.
8. 	Recording
8.1 Straight-Beam Examination — Record the follow-
ing indications as information for the purchaser. These
recordable indications do not constitute a rejectable condi-
tion unless negotiated as such in the purchase order.
8.1.1 	In the back-reflection technique, individual
indications equal to or exceeding 10% of the back reflection
from an adjacent area free from indications; in the refer-
ence-block or DGS technique, indications equal to or
exceeding 100% of the reference amplitude.
8.1.2 	An indication that is continuous on the same
plane regardless of amplitude, and found over an area larger
than twice the diameter of the search unit. The extent of
such an indication shall be accurately measured along with
variations in amplitudes of reflections.
8.1.2.1 Planar indications shall be considered con-
tinuous over a plane if they have a major axis greater than
1 in. [25 mm]. In recording these indications, corrections
must be made for beam divergence at the estimated flaw
depth.
8.1.3 	In the back-reflection technique, discontinuity
indications equal to or exceeding 5% of the back reflection.
In the reference-block technique, indications equal to or
exceeding 50% of the reference amplitude providing that
they travel, are continuous, or appear as clusters.
8.1.3.1 Traveling indications are herein defined as
indications whose leading edge moves a distance equiva-
lent to 1 in. [25 mm] or more of metal depth with movement
of the search unit over the surface of the forging.
8.1.3.2 	A cluster of indications is defined as five
or more indications located in a volume representing a
2 in. [50 mm] or smaller cube in the forging.
8.1.4 	Reduction in back reflection exceeding 20%
of the original measured in increments of 10%.
8.1.5 Amplitudes of recordable indications in incre-
ments of 10%.
8.2 Angle-Beam Examination — Record discontinuity
indications equal to or exceeding 50% of the indication
from the reference line. When an amplitude reference line
cannot be generated, record discontinuity indications equal
to or exceeding 50% of the reference notch. These
recordable indications do not constitute a rejectable condi-
tion unless negotiated as such in the purchase order.
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS

=== PAGE 5 ===
2007 SECTION V 	ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M
9. 	Report
9.1 	Report the following information:
9.1.1 	All recordable indications (see Section 8).
9.1.2 	For the purpose of reporting the locations of
recordable indications, a sketch shall be prepared showing
the physical outline of the forging including dimensions
of all areas not inspected due to geometric configuration,
the purchaser’s drawing number, the purchaser’s order
number, and the manufacturer’s serial number, and the
axial, radial, and circumferential distribution of recordable
ultrasonic indications.
9.1.3 The specification to which the examination was
performed as well as the frequency used, method of setting
sensitivity, type of instrument, surface finish, couplant, and
search unit employed.
9.1.4 	The inspector’s name or identity and date the
examination was performed.
10. 	Quality Levels
10.1 	This practice is intended for application to forg-
ings, with a wide variety of sizes, shapes, compositions,
melting processes, and applications. It is, therefore, imprac-
ticable to specify an ultrasonic quality level which would
be universally applicable to such a diversity of products.
Ultrasonic acceptance or rejection criteria for individual
forgings should be based on a realistic appraisal of service
requirements and the quality that can normally be obtained
in the production of the particular type forging.
10.2 Heavy austenitic stainless steel forgings are more
difficult to penetrate ultrasonically than similar carbon or
low-alloy steel forgings. The degree of attenuation nor-
mally increases with section size; and the noise level, gen-
erally or in isolated areas, may become too great to permit
detection of discrete indications. In most instances, this
attenuation results from inherent coarse grained micro-
structure of these austenitic alloys. For these reasons, the
355
methods and standards employed for ultrasonically exam-
ining carbon and low-alloy steel forgings may not be appli-
cable to heavy austenitic steel forgings. In general, only
straight-beam inspecting using a back-reflection reference
standard is used. However, utilization of Practice A 745/
A 745M for austenitic steel forgings can be considered if
flat-bottom hole reference standards or angle-beam exami-
nation of these grades are required.
10.3 	Acceptance quality levels shall be established
between purchaser and manufacturer on the basis of one
or more of the following criteria.
10.3.1 Straight-Beam Examination:
10.3.1.1 No indications larger than some percent-
age of the reference back reflection.
10.3.1.2 No indications equal to or larger than the
indication received from the flat-bottom hole in a specific
reference block or blocks.
10.3.1.3 No areas showing loss of back reflection
larger than some percentage of the reference back
reflection.
10.3.1.4 	No indications per 10.3.1.1 or 10.3.1.2
coupled with some loss of resultant back reflection per
10.3.1.3.
10.3.1.5 	No indications exceeding the reference
level specified in the DGS method.
10.3.2 Angle-Beam Examination — No indications
exceeding a stated percentage of the reflection from a refer-
ence notch or of the amplitude reference line.
10.4 Intelligent application of ultrasonic quality levels
involves an understanding of the effects of many parame-
ters on examination results.
11. 	Keywords
11.1 	angle beam examination; back-reflection; DGS;
reference-block; straight beam examination; ultrasonic
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--```,``,`,,````,,`,,`,,,`,,,```-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 6 ===
ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M 	2007 SECTION V
SUPPLEMENTARY REQUIREMENTS
The following supplementary requirements shall apply
only when specified by the purchaser in the inquiry, con-
tract, or order. Details shall be agreed upon by the manufac-
turer and the purchaser.
S1. 	REPORTING CRITERIA
S1.1 	Reference block calibration shall be performed
using at least three holes, spaced to approximate minimum,
mean, and maximum thickness as tested, and shall be used
to generate a distance amplitude correction (DAC) curve.
The following hole sizes apply:
356
(a) 1
⁄ 16 in. [1.5 mm] flat bottom holes (FBH) for thick-
nesses less than 1.5 in. [40 mm]
(b) 1
⁄8 in. [3 mm] FBH for thicknesses of 1.5–6 in. [40–
150 mm] inclusive
(c) 1
⁄4 in. [6 mm] FBH for thicknesses over 6 in.
[150 mm]
S1.2 	Reporting criteria include:
(a) all indications exceeding the DAC curve
(b) two or more indications separated by 1
⁄2 in. [12 mm]
or less
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--```,``,`,,````,,`,,`,,,`,,,```-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 7 ===
2007 SECTION V 	ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M
APPENDIXES
(Nonmandatory Information)
X1. 	TYPICAL TUNING LEVEL
COMPENSATION FOR THE EFFECTS OF
FORGING CURVATURE
X1.1 	The curve (Fig. X1.1) was determined for the
following test conditions:
Material 	Nickel-molybdenum-vanadium alloy
steel (Specification A 469, Class 4)
Instrument 	Type UR Reflectoscope
Search unit 	11 / 8 in. [30 mm] diameter quartz
Frequency 	2 1 / 4 MHz
Reference block 	ASTM No. 3-0600 (aluminum)
Reflection area of 	0.010 in. 2 [6.5 mm 2 ] in nickel-molyb-
reference curve 	denum-vanadium alloy steel
Surface finish 	250
in. [6
m] max. roughness
X1.2 	To utilize curve, adjust reflectoscope sensitivity
to obtain indicated ultrasonic response on ASTM No. 3-
0600 reference block for each diameter as shown. A
response of 1 in. [25 mm] sweep-to-peak is used for flat
surfaces. Use attenuator to obtain desired amplitude, but
do testing at 1 to 1 setting.
X2. 	INDICATION AMPLITUDE
COMPENSATION FOR TEST DISTANCE
VARIATIONS
X2.1 	The curve (Fig. X2.1) has been determined for
the following test conditions:
Material 	Nickel-molybdenum-vanadium alloy
steel (Specification A 469, Class 4)
Instrument 	Type UR Reflectoscope
Search unit 	11 / 8 in. [30 mm] diameter quartz
Frequency 	2 1 / 4 MHz
Couplant 	No. 20 oil
Reference block 	ASTM No. 3-0600 (aluminum)
Reflection area of 	0.010 in. 2 [6.5 mm 2 ] in nickel-molyb-
reference curve 	denum-vanadium alloy steel
Surface finish 	250
in. max. roughness
X2.2 To utilize curve, establish amplitude from ASTM
reference block to coincide with values from Appendix X1.
X3. 	BACKGROUND INFORMATION ON THE
DGS METHODS
X3.1 	The DGS method was developed to determine
flaw sizes by comparison to a backwall echo produced on
357
FIG. X1.1 	TYPICAL COMPENSATION CURVE FOR
EFFECTS OF FORGING CURVATURE
the part to be ultrasonic tested. The derivation of DGS
curves is extensively covered and can be found in standard
texts on ultrasonic testing, and will not be covered here.
The distance or thickness of the forging (A) to be tested,
as noted on the overlay, must be accurately defined on the
CRT screen. The back reflection (B) of the part must be
established and suitable gain added. Flaw echo indications
that appear can be sized via the flaw size curves (C) on
the overlay. Item (D) depicts the transducers that the over-
lay works in conjunction with and (E) depicts the series
of curves that the overlay scales are matched to.
X4. 	COMPENSATION FOR CENTER HOLE
ATTENUATION ON CYLINDRICAL BORED
OR HOLLOW FORGINGS UTILIZING THE
DGS METHOD
X4.1 	The hole in a cylindrical bored forging causes
sound scatter. In these cases, a correction is required which
depends on the wall thickness and bore diameter.
X4.1.1 	Determine the correction value in dB from
the Nomogram (Fig. X4.1).
X4.1.2 	Proceed as described in 7.2.2.3.
X4.1.3 	With the GAIN-dB control, reduce the flaw
detector gain by the correction value determined as per the
Nomogram (Fig. X4.2). Thus, the flaw detector gain is
accurately adjusted.
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS

=== PAGE 8 ===
ARTICLE 23, SA-388/SA-388M 	2007 SECTION V
FIG. X2.1 	TYPICAL DISTANCE–AMPLITUDE
CORRECTION CURVE
FIG. X4.2 	THE INFLUENCE OF A CENTRAL BORE ON THE BACKWALL ECHO AMPLITUDE OF CYLINDRICAL OR
PLANE PARALLEL FORGINGS
358
FIG. X4.1 	EXAMPLE OF DGS OVERLAY
Copyright ASME InternationalProvided by IHS under license with ASME	Licensee=Dedini S.A. Industrias de Base/5970143001Not for Resale, 12/18/2007 10:08:36 MST	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--```,``,`,,````,,`,,`,,,`,,,```-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---
