
=== PAGE 1 ===
Designation: E2375 − 16
Standard Practice for
Ultrasonic Testing of Wrought Products 1
This standard is issued under the fixed designation E2375; the number immediately following the designation indicates the year of
original adoption or, in the case of revision, the year of last revision. A number in parentheses indicates the year of last reapproval. A
superscript epsilon (´) indicates an editorial change since the last revision or reapproval.
This standard has been approved for use by agencies of the U.S. Department of Defense.
1. Scope
1.1 Purpose—This practice establishes the minimum re-
quirements for ultrasonic examination of wrought products.
N OTE 1—This standard was adopted to replace MIL-STD-2154, 30
Sept. 1982. This standard is intended to be used for the same applications
as the document which it replaced. Users should carefully review its
requirements when considering its use for new, or different applications,
or both.
1.2 Application—This practice is applicable for examination
of materials such as, wrought metals and wrought metal
products having a thickness or cross section equal to 0.250 in.
(6.35 mm) or greater.
1.2.1 Wrought Aluminum Alloy Products—Examination
shall be in accordance with Practice B594.
1.3 Acceptance Class—When examination is performed in
accordance 	with 	this 	practice, 	engineering 	drawings,
specifications, or other applicable documents shall indicate the
acceptance criteria. Five ultrasonic acceptance classes are
defined in Table 1. One or more of these classes may be used
to establish the acceptance criteria or additional or alternate
criteria may be specified.
1.4 Order of Precedence—Contractual requirements and
authorized direction from the cognizant engineering organiza-
tion may add to or modify the requirements of this practice.
Otherwise, in the event of conflict between the text of this
practice and the references cited herein, the text of this practice
takes precedence. Nothing in this practice, however, super-
sedes applicable laws and regulations unless a specific exemp-
tion has been obtained.
1.5 Measurement Values—The values stated in inch-pounds
are to be regarded as standard. The metric equivalents are in
parentheses.
1.6 This standard does not purport to address all of the
safety concerns, if any, associated with its use. It is the
responsibility of the user of this standard to establish appro-
priate safety and health practices and determine the applica-
bility of regulatory limitations prior to use.
2. Referenced Documents
2.1 The following documents form a part of this practice to
the extent specified herein:
2.2 ASTM Standards:2
B107/B107M Specification for Magnesium-Alloy Extruded
Bars, Rods, Profiles, Tubes, and Wire
B221 Specification for Aluminum and Aluminum-Alloy Ex-
truded Bars, Rods, Wire, Profiles, and Tubes
B241/B241M Specification for Aluminum and Aluminum-
Alloy Seamless Pipe and Seamless Extruded Tube
B594 Practice for Ultrasonic Inspection of Aluminum-Alloy
Wrought Products
E127 Practice for Fabrication and Control of Aluminum
Alloy Ultrasonic Standard Reference Blocks
E164 Practice for Contact Ultrasonic Testing of Weldments
E213 Practice for Ultrasonic Testing of Metal Pipe and
Tubing
E317 Practice for Evaluating Performance Characteristics of
Ultrasonic Pulse-Echo Testing Instruments and Systems
without the Use of Electronic Measurement Instruments
E428 Practice for Fabrication and Control of Metal, Other
than Aluminum, Reference Blocks Used in Ultrasonic
Testing
E543 Specification for Agencies Performing Nondestructive
Testing
E1065 Practice for Evaluating Characteristics of Ultrasonic
Search Units
E1158 Guide for Material Selection and Fabrication of
Reference Blocks for the Pulsed Longitudinal Wave Ul-
trasonic Testing of Metal and Metal Alloy Production
Material
E1316 Terminology for Nondestructive Examinations
1 This practice is under the jurisdiction of ASTM Committee E07 on Nonde-
structive Testing and is the direct responsibility of Subcommittee E07.06 on
Ultrasonic Method.
Current edition approved Dec. 1, 2016. Published January 2017. Originally
approved in 2004. Last previous edition approved in 2013 as E2375 - 08(2013).
DOI: 10.1520/E2375-16.
2 For referenced ASTM standards, visit the ASTM website, www.astm.org, or
contact ASTM Customer Service at service@astm.org. For Annual Book of ASTM
Standards volume information, refer to the standard’s Document Summary page on
the ASTM website.
Copyright © ASTM International, 100 Barr Harbor Drive, PO Box C700, West Conshohocken, PA 19428-2959. United States
This international standard was developed in accordance with internationally recognized principles on standardization established in the Decision on Principles for the
Development of International Standards, Guides and Recommendations issued by the World Trade Organization Technical Barriers to Trade (TBT) Committee.
1	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 2 ===
2.3 American Society for Nondestructive Testing (ASNT)
Standards:
SNT-TC-1A Recommended Practice for Personnel Qualifi-
cation and Certification in Nondestructive Testing3
ANSI/ASNT-CP-189 ASNT Standard for Qualification and
Certification of Nondestructive Testing Personnel3
2.4 Society for Automotive Engineers (SAE) Standards:
AMS 4928 Titanium Alloy, Bars, Wire, Forgings, and Rings
6Al-4V Annealed4
AMS 6409 Steel, Bars, Forgings, and Tubing, 0.80 Cr, 1.8
Ni, 0.25 Mo, (0.38 - 0.45 C), (SAE 4340) Special Aircraft
Steel Cleanliness, Normalized and Tempered4
AMS 6415 Steel, Bars, Forgings, and Tubing, 0.80 Cr, 1.8
Ni, 0.25 Mo (0.38 - 0.43 C) (SAE 4340)4
AMS 6484 Steel, Bars, Forgings, and Tubing, 080 Cr, 1.8
Ni, 0.25 Mo (0.38 - 0.43 C) (SAE 4340) Normalized and
Tempered4
2.5 Aerospace Industries Association Standard:
NAS 410 Certification and Qualification of Nondestructive
Test Personnel5
2.6 Federal Specifications:
QQ-A-225/6 Aluminum Alloy Bar, Rod, and Wire, Rolled,
Drawn, or Cold Finished, 20245
QQ-A-225/9 Aluminum Alloy Bar, Rod, Wire, and Special
Shapes, Rolled, Drawn, or Cold Finished, 70755
2.7 Military Standards:6
N OTE 2—For DoD contracts, unless otherwise specified, the issues of
the documents which are DoD adopted are those listed in the issue of the
DoDISS (Department of Defense Index of Specifications Standards) cited
in the solicitation.
3. Terminology
3.1 Definitions—Definitions 	relating 	to 	ultrasonic
examination, which appear in Terminology E1316, shall apply
to the terms used in this standard.
3.2 Definitions of Terms Specific to This Standard:
3.2.1 display—the display on which ultrasonic data are
presented, including, but is not limited to, cathode ray tubes,
liquid crystals, electro-luminescent phosphors, or plasmas.
3.2.2 full scale deflection (FSD)—the maximum displayable
signal amplitude on the display device, or any signal reaching
or exceeding the 100 % amplitude scale graduation.
3.2.3 horizontal limit—the maximum readable length of
horizontal position that is determined either by electrical or a
physical limit in the A-scan presentation of an ultrasonic
examination instrument.
3.2.4 primary reference response—the maximized signal
amplitude obtained from the applicable reference reflector that
produces the lowest amplitude signal.
3 Available from The American Society for Nondestructive Testing (ASNT), P.O.
Box 28518, 1711 Arlingate Ln., Columbus, OH 43228-0518.
4 Available from Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE), 400 Commonwealth
Dr., Warrendale, PA 15096-0001.
5 Aerospace Industries Association of America, Inc., 1250 Eye Street NW,
Washington, DC 20005.
6 Copies of specifications, standards, drawings and publications required by
manufacturers in connection with specific acquisition functions should be obtained
from the contracting activity or as directed by the contracting officer.
TABLE 1 Ultrasonic Classes
Class 	Single Discontinuity
ResponseA,B
MultipleC
Discontinuities LinearD Discontinuity
Length and Response
Loss of Back
Reflection PercentE,F 	NoiseG,H
AAAH 	25 % of 3 ⁄ 64 in.FB 	10 % of 3 ⁄ 64 in.
(0.119 mm) FB
1 ⁄ 8 in. (3.176 mm) long or 10 % of
3 ⁄ 64 in. (0.119 mm) FB
50 	alarm level
AAH 	3 ⁄ 64 in. (1.19 mm)
FB
2 ⁄ 64 in.I (0.794 mm)
FB
1 ⁄ 2 in. (12. 7 mm)
long
2 ⁄ 64 in. response (0.794 mm)
FB
50 	alarm level
A 	5 ⁄ 64 in. (1.98 mm)
FB
3 ⁄ 64 in. (1.191 mm)
FB
1 in. (25.4 mm)
long
3 ⁄ 64 in. response (1.19 mm)
FB
50 	alarm level
B 	8 ⁄ 64 in. (3.18 mm)
FB
5 ⁄ 64 (1.98 mm)
FB
1 in. (25.4 mm)
long
5 ⁄ 64 in. response (1.98 mm)
FB
50 	alarm level
C 	8 ⁄ 64 in. (3.18 mm) 	Not Applicable 	Not Applicable 	50 	alarm level
A Any discontinuity with a response greater than the response from a flat-bottom hole or equivalent notch (see footnoteB ) at the estimated discontinuity depth and the
discontinuity size given is not acceptable.	
B See Fig. 3, Fig. 4, or Fig. 5 for dimensions of notches and holes when these are required for angle beam examination of tube walls and near-surface regions of cylindrical
parts and other products.
C Multiple discontinuities with indications greater than the response from a reference flat-bottom hole or equivalent notch at the estimated discontinuity depth of the size
given (diameter) are not acceptable if the centers of any two of these discontinuities are less than one inch apart (not applicable to Class C).
D Any discontinuity longer than the length given with indications equal to or greater than the response given (flat-bottom hole or notch response) is not acceptable. Not
applicable to Class C).
E Loss of back reflection by more than 50 %, when compared to non-defective material in the same or a similar part, is not acceptable.
F For longitudinal examination of material over 6-in. (152.4-mm) thick in the short transverse direction, any loss of back reflection equal to or greater than 12 dB over an
area 2 by 2 in. (50.8 by 50.8 mm) is rejectable. (Noise level is not relevant to this back reflection evaluation.
G Noise which exceeds the alarm level setting (see 7.4.10.7), is not acceptable, except for titanium. For titanium alloys, the alarm level may be set just above the noise
level, but shall not exceed 70 % of the reference standard response.
H When examining titanium, Class AA and Class AAA, no rejection shall be made on the basis of “noise” level, if within the limits specified in footnoteG .	
I Evaluation may be done by setting up on a 3 ⁄ 64 in. (1.19 mm) hole and adding 7 dB of gain. (Also see Note 5 under Table 5.)
E2375 − 16
2	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 3 ===
4. Significance and Use
4.1 This practice is intended primarily for the examination
of wrought metals, forged, rolled, machined parts or compo-
nents to an ultrasonic class most typically specified in the
purchase order or other contract document.
5. Basis of Application
5.1 Basis of Application—There are areas in this practice
that may require agreement between the cognizant engineering
organization and the supplier, or specific direction from the
cognizant engineering organization.
6. General Requirements
6.1 Specifying—When ultrasonic examination is specified in
accordance with this practice, the ultrasonic technique
(immersion, contact, angle beam, straight beam, and so forth)
and acceptance criteria should be specified. Suggested classes
in Table 1 may be specified to establish acceptance criteria. A
contract document shall specify zones, when applicable, to
indicate different quality level acceptance criteria based on the
criticality of each zone. When directions of maximum stressing
are indicated on a contract document and configuration allows,
ultrasonic examination shall be performed to locate disconti-
nuities oriented perpendicular to the directions of maximum
stressing.
6.2 Personnel Qualification/Certification—Personnel per-
forming examinations to this practice shall be qualified in
accordance with ANSI/ASNT-CP-189, NAS-410, or SNT-
TC-1A and certified by the employer or certifying agency as
applicable. Other equivalent qualification documents may be
used when specified in the contract or purchase order.
6.3 Agency Evaluation—If required by contract, evaluation
of the agency performing examination shall be in accordance
with Practice E543.
6.4 Written Procedure—A detailed procedure (general
procedure, or part specific technique, or both) shall be prepared
for each part and type of examination to be performed. The
procedure shall meet the requirements of this practice and shall
provide consistency for producing the results and quality level
required by this practice and other contractual documents. The
procedure shall be approved by an individual qualified and
certified as a Level III in the practice of ultrasonic examination.
The procedure shall be submitted upon request to the contract-
ing agency for approval, or review, or both (see 8.1). The
procedure shall cover all of the specific information required to
set-up and perform the examination, such as the following:
6.4.1 Name and address of examination facility,
6.4.2 Number of the procedure including latest revision
designation, if applicable, and date.
6.4.3 Number of this standard including latest revision
designation letter, if applicable, and date.
6.4.4 Examination method and acceptance criteria to be
applied.
6.4.5 Examination zones, if applicable.
6.4.6 Specific part number and configuration or product
form for which the procedure is being prepared.
6.4.7 Manufacturer and model numbers of any instrumen-
tation to be used in the examination. Any external recording
equipment, alarm equipment and electronic distance-amplitude
correction equipment shall be included.
6.4.8 Type and size of search unit. Include frequency, focal
length, as applicable, manufacturer, sound beam angle and
description 	of 	any 	wedges, 	shoes, 	saddles, 	stand-off
attachments, bubblers, or squirters.
6.4.9 Description of manipulating and scanning equipment.
6.4.10 Couplant: type and manufacturer.
6.4.11 Scanning plan which describes, for each portion of
the examination, the surfaces from which the examination will
be performed, the ultrasonic modes, and directions of the sound
beam.
6.4.12 Method of applying transfer (see 7.4.10.4), if ap-
plied.
6.4.13 Reference blocks, water path (if applicable) and
methods of standardization and scan index determination,
maximum scanning speed, and minimum pulse repetition rate.
6.4.14 Method of establishing scan sensitivity for concave
and convex surfaces, if applicable.
6.4.15 Discontinuity evaluation procedure.
6.4.16 Any other pertinent data which would be needed to
duplicate the original examination.
6.5 General Procedures—General procedures are accept-
able for common product forms such as plate, bar stock,
extrusions, forgings, tubing and cylindrical stock, and desig-
nated thickness ranges. The general procedure shall include the
applicable items of 6.4.
7. Detail Requirements
7.1 Couplants:
7.1.1 Immersion Method—For the immersion method (see
7.2.8), water shall be free of air bubbles and other foreign
material that could interfere with ultrasonic examinations. A
suitable corrosion inhibiting agent, or a wetting agent, or both,
shall be added to the water, if necessary. The specific inhibiting
and wetting agents including mixing concentrations shall have
been previously determined to be compatible with the materials
to be examined.
7.1.2 Contact Method—For the contact method, a liquid or
semi-liquid that forms a thin film between the search unit and
the part is required. The couplant material used shall not be
injurious to the material to be examined and will permit
detection of applicable discontinuity sizes. Glycerin (Pure),
silicones and graphite greases shall not be used as couplants,
unless specifically permitted by the cognizant engineering
organization.
7.2 Equipment:
7.2.1 Electronic Equipment—The equipment when used
with appropriate search units shall be capable of producing
ultrasonic examination frequencies as required by the applica-
tion. The electronic equipment shall be calibrated after any
repair or part/component replacement which could affect its
response characteristics, or once each year, whichever occurs
first. Records of the current calibration shall be retained and
available for review.
E2375 − 16
3	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 4 ===
7.2.1.1 The equipment shall meet the following require-
ments as directed in Practice E317 or other approved proce-
dure:
(1) Vertical Limit—100 % of full scale.
(2) Horizontal Limit—100 % of full scale.
(3) Vertical Linearity Limit Range—The vertical linearity
of the instrument shall meet the requirements of A3.3.
(4) Horizontal Linearity Limit Range—The instrument
shall be linear within 65 % of full scale between 0 and 85 %
of the horizontal limit. This step may be omitted if the
instrument is used within a limited depth of material and is
verified on standards of that depth at each standardization.
(5) Calibrated gain controls shall meet the requirements of
A3.2.2 unless an alternate method for verification has been
approved by the cognizant engineering organization.
7.2.1.2 Attenuator and decade switches as applicable shall
meet the requirements of A3.2.
7.2.1.3 If automatic means are used for detection of loss-
of-back reflection amplitude, it shall be demonstrated that the
speed of response of such means is adequate to detect, at actual
scanning speeds, at least a −6 dB reduction in back reflection
signal from an area no larger than the theoretical area of search
unit beam intersection on the near surface of the material. An
alternate method such as a near zone FBH with only the back
wall gated may be used if approved by the Level III of the
cognizant engineering organization.
N OTE 3—This shall be demonstrated by one of the following techniques
or a technique approved by the Level III of the cognizant engineering
organization.
(1) Place on the surface of the material a temporary spot,
consisting of a double layer of masking tape, or other absorp-
tive material, nominally equal to the area of the beam inter-
section on the near surface. The spot shall be passed through
the search unit beam at full scanning speed. When this is done
the means used for loss- of-back signal shall indicate at least
50 % reduction in back signal amplitude.
(2) An alternate method is to use a near zone FBH with
only the back wall gated
7.2.2 Alarm—An instrument used for other than manual
scanning of a part with constant visual observation of the
instrument display shall contain a means for automatically
indicating the presence of a signal that exceeds a predeter-
mined amplitude threshold within a gated time period. The
alarm threshold level shall be adjustable. The alarm means may
be an amplitude, visual, stop-on-defect, part marking or
sorting, analog or digital recording, or other form of indication
of the presence of potential defects. If automatic means are
used for detection of rejectable discontinuities, it shall be
demonstrated during initial standardization that the speed of
response of such means is adequate to detect, at actual
scanning speeds, a rejectable amplitude from a target at any
depth in the examination range.
7.2.3 Voltage Regulator—If fluctuations in line voltage
cause an amplitude change greater than 62.5 % of full scale of
a signal of half full-scale amplitude, a voltage regulator shall
be required on the power source.
7.2.4 Search Units—Search units are acceptable if they
provide the required examination characteristics including
sensitivity, resolution, and penetration. Search units shall have
active dimensions (diameter for circular elements, length for
rectangular elements) equal to or greater than 0.25 in. (6.35
mm). For contact examination of all convex surfaces of 1.5 in.
(38.1 mm) radius or less, and all concave surfaces of 4 in.
(101.6 mm) radius or less, a curved shoe or wedge, made to
match as closely as possible the radius of the part being
examined, shall be required for examination. All search units
shall be serialized. General search unit characteristics are
typically evaluated by the methods described in Guide E1065.
Such evaluation does not necessarily determine suitability for
any specific material evaluation.
7.2.5 Rectangular 	“Paintbrush” 	Search 	Units—
Rectangular “paintbrush” search units shall be allowed for
straight beam longitudinal immersion scanning if it is demon-
strated that the search unit provides the required examination
characteristics specified in this practice or the contract docu-
ment. The written procedures (see 6.4) shall include at least the
additional items specified in 7.2.5.1 through 7.2.5.3.
7.2.5.1 A method shall be established for determining that
the sensitivity profile along the major axis of the search unit
does not vary more than 610 % of the vertical limit when the
sensitivity is adjusted to provide a nominal 50 % response from
a reference reflector (either a steel ball, wire, or flat-bottom
hole) as shown in Fig. 1. The profile shall have been verified
within a period not exceeding twelve months prior to the date
of use of the search unit, unless masking is used to suppress the
peaks. If masking is used, the search unit profile shall have
been verified within a period not exceeding three months prior
to the date of use.
7.2.5.2 A method shall be established for masking the ends
of the search unit, if required, to eliminate over-sensitive
responses as determined in the sensitivity profile, see A4.1.3.
7.2.5.3 A method shall be established for determining effec-
tive beam width. The scan index established in accordance
with 7.4.10.8 shall be based on the beam width so determined.
7.2.5.4 The reference standard shall provide a uniform entry
surface for the full extent of the sound beam for equipment
standardization.
7.2.5.5 A method shall be established to use the least active
portion of the search unit to adjust scan sensitivity at each
portion of the DAC (Distance Amplitude Correction) curve to
be used.
7.2.5.6 Search units meeting the requirements of 7.2.4 shall
be used for evaluations of indications detected while scanning
with paintbrush search units.
7.2.6 Array Search Units—Array search units (multiple-
element) may be used for initial immersion scanning provided
each element is pulsed independently and produces a beam that
sufficiently overlaps each adjacent beam so that the maximum
allowable drop in signal amplitude between elements is not
more than 3 dB from the peak response (when the peak is set
to 80 % of full scale using the primary reference response for
the applicable examination as the reference reflector). Varia-
tions from these requirements are acceptable for phased array
search units.
E2375 − 16
4	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 5 ===
7.2.7 Focused Search Units—Focused search units may be
used unless otherwise specified in the contract or purchase
order documentation.
7.2.8 Tank—Tanks used for immersion examination shall be
of sufficient size to permit submersion of the part, material, or
the area of interest to be examined with proper orientation of
the search unit and allow sufficient water path.
7.2.8.1 Attachments—For special applications attachments
may be used with the search unit to provide the required water
path distances or coupling.
7.2.9 Manipulating 	Equipment—For 	immersion
examination, manipulating equipment shall adequately support
a search unit and shall provide angular adjustment within one
degree in two planes and demonstrate control for following
part geometry. Examinations not requiring angulation shall be
documented on the scan plan. The bridge shall have sufficient
strength to provide rigid support for the manipulator and shall
allow smooth, accurate positioning of the search unit. The
scanning accuracy of the apparatus shall permit adjustment of
the scan index distance within 60.1 in. (2.54 mm), or unless
otherwise specified by the cognizant engineering organization.
Water travel distance shall be adjustable. When part size, or
configuration, or both, prevent the use of manipulating
equipment, search unit stand-off attachments which provide for
control of water travel distance and sound beam angle shall be
used. Provisions shall be made to ascertain that wear of
stand-off attachments does not exceed limits which will de-
grade the examination.
7.3 Reference Block Fabrication—Reference blocks with
flat-bottom holes with diameters equal to those specified in the
acceptance criteria shall be used for defect detection and
evaluation unless alternate hole sizes are used in accordance
with 7.3.2. The blocks shall meet the response characteristics
of and be certified to the requirements of Practice E127, E428,
E1158, as specified in 7.3.1 through 7.3.9.6 of this practice, or
to the documented requirements of the cognizant engineering
organization. IIW-type blocks shall be certified with respect to
alloy and dimensions specified on the purchase order.
7.3.1 Reference Block Materials—Reference blocks should
be fabricated from the same alloy, surface finish and heat
treatment as the part to be examined. Where this is not
FIG. 1 Acceptable Sound Beam Profile of “Paintbrush” Search Unit
E2375 − 16
5	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 6 ===
available, or practical, reference blocks may be fabricated from
materials listed in Table 2 so that any ultrasonic transmission
differences are minimized. Other material may be used for
working reference blocks provided the velocity and attenuation
difference between the reference block and the examination
material are within the limits shown below:
7.3.1.1 The longitudinal wave velocity of the material for a
reference standard for straight beam (normalized longitudinal
wave) shall be within 610 % of the velocity of the examina-
tion material. Material for reference standards to be used for
angle beam examination shall have a velocity, in the propaga-
tion mode to be employed, that is within 65 % of that of the
examination material. This may be determined by comparing
the sweep distance, on the ultrasonic instrument display, of
back or end reflections from equal thicknesses of reference
block and examination material.
7.3.1.2 The back or end surface reflections of the examina-
tion material shall be within +4 dB (160 %) to −12 dB (25 %)
of the reference block material corrected to the depth of
examination. Transfer in accordance with 7.4.10.4 is not
allowed if the differences are greater than these limits unless a
documented plan adequately compensates for the cause and is
approved by the cognizant engineering organization.
7.3.1.3 Material to be used for the fabrication of reference
blocks shall be scanned ultrasonically in the mode(s) to be used
in the examination at a sufficiently high sensitivity to detect
any existing anomalies that might produce signals that could
obscure, or be confused with, those from holes, notches or
other targets in the reference block to be fabricated.
7.3.2 Alternate Flat-bottom Hole Sizes—If blocks with the
specified flat-bottom hole sizes are not available, alternative
sizes may be used provided the instrument gain is changed by
a factor given by the ratio of the areas of the two relevant holes.
For cases where only a larger size is available, the gain must be
increased by the ratio (dr / da )2
, where dr and da are respectively
the diameters of the reference and specified acceptance flat-
bottom holes (see Table 5, Note 1). With instruments having
gain controls calibrated in dB, the required change is given by
40 × log(dr / da ) dB. Table 5 can be used for the extrapolation
of gain between any standard hole sizes in the range of 1 ⁄64
through 8 ⁄64. Gain extrapolation shall be restricted to hole
diameters having ratios no greater than 2:1, requiring gain
changes no greater than 12 dB. For class AAA only, gain
extrapolation shall be restricted to hole diameters having ratios
no greater than 3:1, requiring gain changes no greater than 19
dB.
7.3.3 Curved Surface Reference Blocks—Blocks used on
cylindrically or irregularly shaped products shall meet the
following requirements:
7.3.3.1 Examination of Cylindrical Parts of Greater Than 4
in. (101.6 mm) Radius—Reference blocks shall be of material
specified in 7.3.1 and shall be the stepped type shown in Fig.
2 (with correspondingly larger dimensions) or, of the type
specified in 7.3.2 machined to within 10 % of the radius of
curvature of the part being examined, or of the alternate type
described in 7.3.7 in which case larger holes may be used to
clear a holding fixture for the flat-bottom hole drill as described
in 7.3.3.2.
7.3.3.2 Examination of Cylindrical Parts of Less Than 4 in.
(101.6 mm) Radius—Reference blocks shall have a radius of
curvature within 10 % of those parts. The blocks shall be,
where practical, of full round cross-section. Reference holes
may be drilled by using a larger diameter hole drilled to no
closer than 0.5 in. (12.7 mm) to the final depth of the
flat-bottom hole, permitting the use of a holding fixture for the
drill for the flat-bottom holes. An acceptable alternate to full
round blocks is the stepped type shown in Fig. 2. Flat-bottom
holes, of the sizes required for the appropriate examination
class in accordance with Table 1, shall be placed in the block
at the metal travel distances specified in 7.4.7.1. The sizes and
depths of the flat-bottom holes shall be verified by calibrated
measuring instruments and the holes should be plugged to
prevent water entry and to create an air interface at the hole
bottom. If it is not possible to use the same material for
reference blocks, the provisions of 7.3.1 shall apply.
TABLE 2 Recommended Reference Block Material
Material to be 	Reference
Material
Typical
Specification
Aluminum 	7075-T6 	ASTM B221
ASTM B241/
B241M
QQ-A225/9
2024 	ASTM B221
ASTM B241/
B241M
QQ-A225/6
Magnesium 	ZK60 	ASTM B107/
B107M
Titanium 	T1-6A1-4V annealed 	AMS 4928
Low-Alloy Steels
(4130, 4340);
High-Strength Low-
Steels
(such as NAX,
T-300M);
Straight Carbon and
H-11 Tool
4340 annealed 	AMS 6484
AMS 6415
AMS 6409
N OTE 1—Other materials may be used when documented and approved
by the cognizant engineering organization.
TABLE 3 Surface Resolution Requirements
Material Thickness (t) 	Resolution Requirements
Forgings/Re-Forgings 	Other Materials
Up to 1.25 in. (31.75
mm) 1 ⁄ 4 in. (6.35 mm) 	1 ⁄ 8 in. (3.05 mm)
1.25 in.(31.75) and over 	1 ⁄ 4 in. (6.35 mm) 	1 ⁄ 10 t
2.5 in. (63.5 mm) and
over 1 ⁄ 10 t or 1 ⁄ 2 in. (12.7 mm), whichever is less
N OTE 1—Unless otherwise specified in a contract document.
TABLE 4 Flat Surface Reference Standard Metal Travel
Depth of
Discontinuity,
in. (mm)
Reference Standard Metal
Travel Distance Tolerance,
in. (mm)
Up to 1 ⁄ 4 (6.35)
0.250 (6.35) to 1.0 (25.4)
1.0 (25.4) to 3 (76.2)
3.0 (76.2) to 6 (152.4)
Over 6.0 (152.4)
±1 ⁄ 16 (1.59)
± 1 ⁄ 8 (3.18)
± 1 ⁄ 4 (6.35)
± 1 ⁄ 2 (12.7)
±10 % of metal travel
E2375 − 16
6	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 7 ===
7.3.3.3 Alternate Tolerances for Straight-Beam Examina-
tion of Cylindrical Parts—In the case of straight-beam exami-
nation only, where detection of indications of the class speci-
fied is demonstrated to the satisfaction of the cognizant
engineering organization, the cognizant Level 3, and
documented, the use of reference standards with greater
departure of radius from that of the test material than that listed
above, may be permitted.
N OTE 4—The use of round cross-section blocks allows the dynamic
verification of instrument and system standardization. Such dynamic
verification may be difficult, or not possible, using stepped blocks.
7.3.4 Rectangular Angle Beam Reference Blocks—Fig. 3 is
the configuration for rectangular angle beam blocks using
flat-bottom holes for use with contact examination only.
Side-drilled holes may be used to obtain graphic distance-
amplitude curves with sensitivity corrected by using the
end-drilled holes of the applicable ultrasonic class size (see
A1.3.4). Other block configurations and reflectors may be used
if they meet the requirements of 7.3.7 and 7.3.8, or comply
with documented requirements approved by the cognizant
engineering organization. The vee-path options illustrated in
Fig. A1.4 shall not be used to obtain standardization of
immersion examinations because of the loss of sound energy at
the apex of the vee-paths if the block is immersed.
7.3.5 Hollow Cylindrical Angle Beam Reference Blocks—
Reference blocks for shear wave examination of tubing and
ring forgings shall have an outer ring diameter that is within
65 % of the outside diameter of the examination material and
the thickness shall be 610 % of the examination material. The
reference block shall contain reference reflector notches in
accordance with Fig. 4 based on the applicable class of
examination in accordance with Table 1.
7.3.6 International Institute of Welding (IIW) Type Refer-
ence Block—Blocks derived from the International Institute of
Welding (IIW), Reference Block, Practice E164 Annex A, shall
be used for evaluation of contact angle beam search units as an
aid in determining proper positioning for contact angle beam
examination, and to determine beam exit point from the search
units and angle of the sound beam. The material from which
the blocks are to be made must be specified by the purchaser.
7.3.7 Alternate 	Reference 	Blocks—Other 	reference
reflectors, as approved by the cognizant engineering organiza-
tion may be used.
7.3.8 Alternate Reference Block Fabrication—If other types
of reference blocks, reflectors and materials are used as
approved by the cognizant engineering organization, material
for these blocks shall meet the requirements of 7.3.1 and,
where applicable, reference targets shall meet the requirements
of 7.3.7.
7.3.9 Additional Fabrication Requirements—The following
additional fabrication/verification requirements apply to refer-
ence blocks specified herein:
TABLE 5 Appropriate dB Gain Changes between Flat-Bottom Hole (FBH) Sizes
Acceptable Flat-Bottom
Hole Diameter,
1 ⁄ 64 in. (mm)
Reference Flat-Bottom Hole Diameter, 1 ⁄ 64 in. (mm)
1
(0.4)
2
(0.8)
3
(1.2)
4
(1.6)
5
(2.0)
6
(2.4)
7
(2.8)
8
(3.2)
1
(0.4)
0 dB 	+12 dB
2
(0.8)
−12 dB 	0 dB 	+7 dB 	+12 dB
3
(1.2)
−7 dB 	0 dB 	+5 dB 	+9 dB 	+12 dB
4
(1.6)
−12 dB 	−5 dB 	0 dB 	+4 dB 	+7 dB 	+10 dB 	+12 dB
5
(2.0)
−9 dB 	−4 dB 	0 dB 	+3 dB 	+6 dB 	+8 dB
6
(2.4)
−12 dB 	−7 dB 	−3 dB 	0 dB 	+3 dB 	+5 dB
7
(2.8)
−10 dB 	−6 dB 	−3 dB 	0 dB 	+2 dB
8
(3.2)
−12 dB 	−8 dB 	−5 dB 	−2 dB 	0 dB
N OTE 1—Blank areas contain absolute values of gain changes greater than 612 dB and are not applicable, see 7.3.1.1.
N OTE 2—Reference FBH diameter refers to the size of the FBH in the reference blocks. Acceptance FBH diameter refers to the extrapolated FBH. Table
entries are calculated as follows:
40 log10 S reference FBH diameter
acceptance FBH diameterD 5 dB
N OTE 3— +dB = instrument gain increase; −dB = instrument gain decrease.
N OTE 4—If the dB control has a minimum incremental change of 2 dB and the extrapolation requires an uneven dB change, the dB control shall be
adjusted for 1 dB more gain than required. For instance, in this case note the dB control in Note 5 would be increased by +10 dB instead of +9 dB.
N OTE 5—Explanation of Extrapolation: With a reference FBH of 5 ⁄ 64 in. (1.98 mm) and an acceptance FBH of 3 ⁄ 64 in. (1.191 mm), the difference is
+9 dB. Since the acceptance FBH is smaller than the reference FBH, the gain must be increased by 9 dB from the reference FBH setting.
N OTE 6—This table assumes a linear relationship between the amplitude of the response of an instrument and the area of a flat-bottom hole target. This
assumption is approximately valid only for certain material configurations and combinations of search units and instrument parameters.
E2375 − 16
7	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 8 ===
7.3.9.1 Flat-bottom holes shall be dimensionally evaluated
in accordance with Practice E428. As an alternate, the holes
may be verified in accordance with Practice E127.
7.3.9.2 The angular alignment of holes in reference blocks
shall have a tolerance of 630 min and be perpendicular to the
beam entry surface or other surface or direction as required or
intended by the governing specification.
7.3.9.3 Reference standards shall be clearly identified so
that the hole size, depth and material type (refracted angle, if
used) are discerned on the block or a drawing of the block. If
N OTE 1—Primary units are inches, ( ) are millimetres.
N OTE 2—An approved alternate configuration to that of Fig. 2 is to divide and construct each of the ten reference blocks as three separate blocks; one
containing the “C” dimensions, one containing the “B” dimensions, and one containing the “A” dimensions. For this alternate construction, all dimensions
of Fig. 2 apply except as follows:
(1) For each C block, the F dimension shall equal the listed E dimension.
(2) For each B block, the F dimension and the sketched 0.5 in. (12.7 mm) dimension shall be 1.0 in. (25.4 mm).
(3) For each A block, the sketched 0.5 in. (12.7 mm) dimension shall be 1.0 in. (25.4 mm).
(4) The I thickness shows an alternate design based on the H dimension.
N OTE 3—Alternate forms and dimensions of reference standards may be used in accordance with 7.3.3 that contain only the flat-bottom hole diameter(s)
necessary to meet Table 1 requirements for the specified examination class and which contain metal travel distances to meet 7.4.7.1 and that have radii
of curvature to meet 7.3.1.2.
FIG. 2 Typical Convex Reference Block Configuration for Longitudinal Wave Examination
E2375 − 16
8	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 9 ===
this data is only on the drawing then the reference standard
shall be traceable to its drawing.
7.3.9.4 All reference blocks shall be visually examined prior
to each use for signs of surface and sealing-plug damage or
N OTE 1—A block fabricated with flat-bottom holes with diameters as shown will cover all classes in this practice. A narrower block with fewer holes
may be used if the block is to be used for a fewer number of classes.
NOTE 2—Side-drilled holes shall not be used for T less than 3 ⁄ 4 in. (19.05 mm).
N OTE 3—A shorter block than shown may be used for thicker materials when only 1 ⁄ 2 or 1 vee-path examining distance is to be used. For shorter
reference blocks the side-drilled holes shall be relocated along L so that each hole lies at least 3 ⁄ 4 in. from all sound beam paths used for the other holes.
N OTE 4—D = hole diameter for applicable class.
N OTE 5—θ is the nominal angle of the sound beam in the part with respect to the normal to the sound entry surface. Typical examples: θ = 60° for
T = (1 ⁄ 2 in. (12.7 mm) to 1 in. (25.4 mm)) and θ = 45° for T = (Over 1 in.).
N OTE 6—φ is the angle of the entering sound beam with respect to the normal to the sound entry surface.
N OTE 7—Primary dimensions are in inches, metric (XX mm).
N OTE 8—All dimensions 6 0.03 in. (0.762 mm) except for hole diameters which are 63 % of diameter specified.
N OTE 9—Surface A and Surface B must be flat and within 0.001 in. per in. (0.025 mm per mm).
N OTE 10—For blocks thicker than one inch, additional 5 ⁄ 64 in. (1.98 mm) diameter side-drilled holes shall be drilled from Surface C with the axes of
the holes located 1 ⁄ 4 in. (6.35 mm), 1 ⁄ 2 in. (12.7 mm), 1 in. (25.4 mm), 1-1 ⁄ 2 in. (38.1 mm) and so forth, from surface A until the T/4 distance is reached.
No specific location along L is required for these holes except that they shall be located at least 3 ⁄ 4 in. (19.05 mm) from the sound beam paths used for
other side-drilled holes.
N OTE 11—All holes should be permanently plugged in a manner to ensure that they are water-tight and that an air-metal interface is preserved.
FIG. 3 Typical Reference Block for Angle Beam Examination
UT Class
Notch Size
(Solid Bars)
DepthA × Length,B in. (mm)
Notch Size
(Tubes)
DepthA × Length,B in. (mm)
AAA 	0.004 (0.10) × 0.188 (4.76) 	3 % of WallC × 0.063 ± 0.005 (1.60 ± 0.13)
AA 	0.005 (0.13) × 0.250 (6.35) 	5 % of WallD × 0.250 (6.35)
A 	0.100 (2.54) × 0.500 (12.7) 	10 % of WallE × 0.500 (12.7)
B 	0.150 (3.81) × 1.000 (25.4) 	12.5 % of WallF × 1.000 (25.4)
C 	Not Applicable 	Not Applicable
A Depth tolerance = ±0.0005 in. (± 0.013 mm) for notches 0.005 in. (0.13 mm) or less in depth, and = +10 %, −15 % for notches over 0.005 in. (0.13 mm) depth, except
as noted.
B Length tolerance = ± 0.010 in. (± 0.254 mm) except as noted.
C 3 % of wall or 0.003 in. (0.076 mm) whichever is greater.
D 5 % of wall or 0.004 in. (0.102 mm) whichever is greater.
E 10 % of wall or 0.004 in. (0.102 mm) whichever is greater.
F 12.5 % of wall or 0.004 in. (0.102 mm) whichever is greater.
N OTE 1—Notch width to be as small as practical but shall not exceed twice the nominal notch depth.
FIG. 4 Rectangular Notch for Angular Beam Reference Reflectors
E2375 − 16
9	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 10 ===
deterioration. Any block which exhibits significant rusting,
corrosion or surface damage, which may interfere with the
examination process, shall be either discarded and replaced, or
cleaned and recertified in accordance with Practice E127,
E428, or the original surface finish requirements as appropri-
ate.
7.3.9.5 After all flat-bottom holes are verified, they shall be
plugged as specified in Practice E127 or E428, to protect the
hole from corrosion when that is a potential problem.
7.3.9.6 Reference standards shall be dried, or couplant
removed, or both, after use. Reference standards shall be
handled and stored in a manner to preclude damage.
7.4 Examination Procedures:
7.4.1 Visual Examination—Prior to ultrasonic examination
visually examine the part or material for cleanliness, surface
roughness, cracks, burrs, nicks, gouges, raised areas, irregular
machining and tool tears. Any surface anomalies that will
impair ultrasonic examination shall be removed prior to
examination. If removal is not possible or practical, mark such
discrepancies on the part for later analysis during evaluation of
ultrasonic indications.
7.4.2 Coverage—The sound beam direction required for
examination of various wrought shapes shall be in accordance
with Figs. 6 and 7. Additional coverage requirements shall be
as specified below:
7.4.2.1 When directions of maximum stressing are indicated
on contract documents, scanning shall be performed to locate
discontinuities that are oriented perpendicular to the specified
directions (see 6.1).
7.4.2.2 When entry surface resolution is not sufficient to
resolve discontinuities near the part surface, as required by
Table 3, while achieving at least a 2:1 or greater signal-to-noise
ratio, additional examinations shall be performed from the
opposite side, or, different examination zone depths shall be
established, or the examination frequency may be changed as
long as all other requirements are met. Also, for each exami-
nation direction, examinations from opposite sides are required
when the maximum metal travel distance is such that the
UT
Class
Hole Diameter / Depth, in. (mm)
Multiple 	Single
A 	0.020 (0.508) diameter / 0.25 (6.35) depth 	0.020 (0.508) diameter / 0.50 (12.70) depth
B 	0.020 (0.508) diameter / 0.50 (12.70) depth 	0.047 (1.19) diameter / 1.00 (25.4) depth
C 	Not Applicable 	0.047 (1.19) diameter / 1.00 (25.4) depth
N OTE 1—Tolerance for location of side-drilled holes is 60.010 in. (0.254 mm).
N OTE 2—All surfaces Roughness = 125 Ra.
NOTE 3—Multiple and single discontinuity size and spacing requirements are defined in Table 1.
N OTE 4—Since reflections are from the hole side, hole bottoms need not be flat.
Diameter of FBH for which
Side-Drilled Hole is to be Substituted, in. (mm)
Side-Drilled Hole (A, B, C, E, F, and G)
Diameter
± 0.001 in. (± 0.025 mm)
Depth
± 0.020 in. (± 0.503 mm)
3 ⁄ 64 (1.190) 	0.020 (0.508) 	0.25 (6.35)
5 ⁄ 64 (1.980) 	0.020 (0.508) 	0.50 (12.7)
8 ⁄ 64 (3.175) 	0.047 (1.190) 	1.00 (25.4)
N OTE 5—Side-drilled holes may be used when specified, but are not necessarily equivalent. Holes should be plugged to keep out dirt and water.
FIG. 5 Side-Drilled-Hole Reference Block
E2375 − 16
10	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 11 ===
minimum size discontinuity of the applicable class cannot be
detected by examination from only one side.
7.4.2.3 When the length of any of the examination dimen-
sions (distance sound beam travels through the material)
exceeds 18 in. (457 mm) supplementary examinations may be
additionally required to locate discontinuities that are not
detectable by straight beam examination. This is based on the
fact that it would be very difficult to detect discontinuities
greater than 9 in. (228 mm) in depth for a Class A, or higher,
examination. It shall be verified that the side walls do not give
erroneous examination results.
7.4.3 Scanning Speed—The scanning speed shall not exceed
the maximum scanning speed which provides for detection of
the reference reflectors in the reference standards used to set up
the examination.
7.4.4 Ultrasonic Frequency—Standardization and examina-
tion shall be performed at the ultrasonic frequency which will
provide the penetration and resolution required for valid
examination of the production material. Examination per-
formed with transmitting and receiving search units of different
frequencies shall be considered to be performed at the fre-
quency of the transmitting search unit for broadband systems.
FIG. 6 Sound Beam Direction for Various Shapes
E2375 − 16
11	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 12 ===
For tuned systems, the operating system frequency is estab-
lished by either the transmitting or receiving system whichever
is tuned.
7.4.5 Water Travel Path for Immersion Method—The dis-
tance from the face of the search unit to the front surface of a
part shall be such that the second front reflection from the
examination material does not appear between the first front
and first back reflections. This distance (water travel) must be
the same within 60.25 in. (66.35 mm) for standardization,
initial scanning and final evaluation. When possible, examina-
tion shall be performed using water paths that result in
examinations being performed in the far field of the search
unit, or in the depth of field of a focused search unit approved
by the cognizant engineering organization. When focused
search units are used, the distance shall be such that the search
unit focus is within the material at the depth required to meet
front surface resolution requirements. For angle beam exami-
nation of curved or cylindrical parts the water path distance
must be maintained at a length which does not vary during
material examination or between standardization and examina-
tion by more than 60.02 times the radius of curvature of the
material.
7.4.6 Lateral Position Stability for Examination of Cylindri-
cal Parts—During dynamic scanning, variation in position of
the vertical centerline of a flat or focused search unit beam with
respect to a radius perpendicular to that centerline shall not
exceed 60.02 times the radius of curvature.
7.4.7 Reference Blocks—Select reference blocks that have
been prepared in accordance with 7.3 with flat-bottom-hole
(FBH) diameters or reference reflectors for the applicable class
(Table 1). Diameters other than specified may be used provided
the diameters are within a factor of two and, after the response
from the reflector is set to be not less than 80 % FSD, or other
amplitude approved by the cognizant engineering organization,
FIG. 7 Sound Beam Direction for Various Shapes
E2375 − 16
12	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 13 ===
and the gain is adjusted by an amount equal to the ratio of the
areas of the two reflectors. The examination shall be performed
at the equivalent gain level for the specified hole.
7.4.7.1 Reference Block Metal Path Increments—Select ref-
erence block(s) containing at least three of the following metal
paths distances, unless an alternate plan demonstrates, and is
approved by the cognizant engineering organization, that only
the extremes of the examination depth of interest are necessary:
(1) A metal path equal to or less than the front surface
resolution. When examination is performed from both surfaces
of a part, or if solid cylindricals are rotated during examination,
examination of only the center-to-far-wall region of the part
may be used if defect detection is demonstrated.
(2) A metal path equal to half of the examination piece or
zone thickness 60.125 in. (3.2 mm).
(3) A metal path equal to or greater than the thickness of
the part or zone to be examined.
(4) When examining parts greater than 2 in. (50.8 mm)
thickness or diameter, reference reflectors shall be provided
with metal paths throughout the examination zone at intervals
sufficient to establish total gain requirements and amplitude
interpolation.
7.4.8 Preparation for Standardization:
7.4.8.1 Immersion—Using the reference blocks selected in
accordance with 7.3, immerse the reference standards and
search unit in the water bath. Normalize the search unit to
maximize the reflected signal from the water-metal interface by
manipulating the search unit.
7.4.8.2 Contact—Using the reference standards selected in
7.3, apply the couplant selected in accordance with 7.1.2.
7.4.9 Use of Reference Curve and Direct Comparison Meth-
ods for Standardization—Standardization of the examination
shall be accomplished by determining the distance-amplitude
relationship for the reference blocks selected in 7.4.7. Com-
pensation for the variation of detection sensitivity with distance
from the entry surface shall be accomplished by using either
the reference curve method of 7.4.9.1, the direct comparison
method of 7.4.9.2, or electronic distance-amplitude correction
(EDAC) as described in 7.4.10.2 and 7.4.10.3.
7.4.9.1 Reference Curve Method—Position the search unit
on each reference block and maximize the signal amplitude.
Set the instrument to achieve the required resolution (for
example, pulse length and tuning). Select the reference stan-
dard that provides the largest amplitude and adjust the gain to
obtain an indication that is not less than 80 % FSD or other
approved amplitude. Mark the amplitude of the maximized
indication from each reference standard on the display and
connect the points with a smooth curve. When material
thickness and attenuation do not permit the above, zoning and
multiple curves or examination from the opposite side may be
required. Once this is done, display time based controls (for
example, sweep delay and length) shall not be changed.
7.4.9.2 Direct Comparison Method—Use block(s) with the
proper hole sizes at sufficient metal travel depth to establish the
gain relation of the beam profile throughout the full examina-
tion depth.
7.4.10 Establishment of Scanning Gain, Index, and Alarm
Level for Standardization—Determine the gain setting for
initial scanning with or without electronic distance-amplitude
correction (EDAC). For the applicable class, the multiple
discontinuity hole size of Table 1 shall be used to establish the
scanning gain, index, and alarm level, except for Class C,
where the single discontinuity hole size shall be used.
7.4.10.1 Scanning Gain without EDAC—Set the initial scan-
ning gain by selecting the reference standard that provides the
lowest echo amplitude on the distance-amplitude curve as
determined by either method of 7.4.9. Maximize the amplitude
from the reference reflector in this reference block, and adjust
the instrument gain to obtain an amplitude not less than 80 %,
or other approved amount, of the upper linearity limit. If
required, adjust the gain as determined by the transfer
technique, 7.4.10.4. This gain setting is the initial scanning
gain level.
7.4.10.2 Scanning Gain with EDAC—For systems that em-
ploy time-varying gain amplifiers, adjust the gain compensa-
tion control so that the indication amplitudes of the reference
reflectors in all reference blocks selected in accordance with
7.4.7 are equalized so that the lowest amplitude is not less than
80 % or other approved amount of the upper linearity limit. If
required, add any gain determined by the transfer technique
(see 7.4.10.4). This is the initial scanning gain level. For
systems that employ time-varying trigger level controls, select
the reference block with a metal path to the reference reflector
that provides the highest echo amplitude on the distance-
amplitude curve as determined in 7.4.9. Maximize the ampli-
tude from the reference reflector in this block, and adjust the
instrument gain to obtain an amplitude equal to 80 % of the
upper linearity limit. If required, add any gain determined by
the transfer technique. This is the initial scanning gain level.
7.4.10.3 Electronic 	Distance-Amplitude 	Correction
(EDAC)—When using EDAC, the reject control shall be off
and the responses from the reference standard reflectors at
metal distances throughout the range corresponding to part
thickness shall be equalized in so far as possible. The lowest
response from any of these reflectors, after DAC correction,
shall be set to be not less than 80 % FSD or other approved
amplitude. Reproducibility shall be verified as specified in
7.5.1.
7.4.10.4 Transfer Technique—The transfer technique shall
be used to compensate for differences in sound transmission
characteristics that may exist between the reference standards
and each part or piece of material to be examined. The transfer
technique may be omitted, when approved by the cognizant
engineering organization, if not applicable or if another com-
pensation method is more appropriate. Transfer shall be ac-
complished by noting the dB or gain difference in the responses
received from reflectors in the reference block and the part or
piece of material to be examined. These reflectors may be the
back surfaces for straight beam examinations, corners for angle
beam examinations, or any other reflectors which will aid in
accomplishing transfer. If possible, a minimum of four reflec-
tions from different locations in the part or piece of material to
be examined shall be noted and the lowest response shall be
used for comparison with the response from the reference
standard. The instrument response shall be corrected by first
standardizing on the applicable reference blocks and then
E2375 − 16
13	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 14 ===
changing the gain or dB of the instrument by the difference in
gain or dB noted above.
(1) Material Thickness—The thickness of the specimen
(parallel to the ultrasonic beam) shall be measured such that at
least two back surface reflections can be resolved at the
frequency of interest. The area normal to the ultrasonic beam
shall have sufficient width so that sidewall echoes do not
interfere with the measurement.
(2) Exception—The use of the transfer technique is not
required for establishing scanning sensitivity if the signal
amplitude from a reflector in each part of each piece of
examination material is in the range between 60 and 160 % of
the signal amplitude from an equivalent reflector in the
reference standard, for example:
0.6A1 # A2 # 1.6A1
or, in decibels,
24 # 20log~A2 /A1! # 4
where:
A1 	= amplitude of the first reflection from a reflector in
reference block material, and
A2 	= amplitude of the first reflection from an equivalent
reflector in the material being examined.
7.4.10.5 Resolution—After scanning gain is established in
accordance with 7.4.10, and if the examination zone includes
the front entry surface, ascertain that the required front surface
resolution, as listed in Table 3, is obtained.
7.4.10.6 Alarm—When examining parts or material with
regular shape and parallel surfaces such as plate, bar stock and
forged billets, an audible alarm, stop-on-discontinuity,
recorder, or other form of alarm shall be used in conjunction
with visual monitoring of the ultrasonic instrument display. If
the examination is computer controlled with result print-out, or
if the results are otherwise automatically recorded, visual
monitoring is not required. When recordings are made, or when
systems stop on discontinuities, the audible alarm is not
required. Triggering of the alarm shall be controlled by
received ultrasonic signals over an adjustable time interval
representing the examination zone.
7.4.10.7 Alarm Level Setting—For examination methods as
in 7.4.11.1 and 7.4.11.2, adjust the alarm to trigger at 50 % of
the standardization level. This corresponds to one half of the
indication amplitude of the lowest point on the distance-
amplitude curve, or the smallest response if the direct com-
parison method is used.
7.4.10.8 Scanning Index Determination—Using the refer-
ence blocks selected in 7.4.7, and the search unit as required by
7.2.4 through 7.2.6, as applicable, determine the maximum
scan index as follows. Maximize the echo amplitude from the
primary reference response and adjust the amplitude so that it
is equal to that used for standardization. Determine the total
traversing distance in the index direction across this reference
block through which no less than half (−6 dB) of the maximum
amplitude is obtained. This is the effective beam width. Select
the block in which the minimum effective beam width of the
search unit is obtained. The scan index shall not exceed an
amount that, under any random beam-to-reference reflector
alignment, will allow the signal from that reference to vary by
more than the 2:1 reject-to-alarm level ratio as specified in
7.4.10.7. (For FBH detection this may be accomplished, as a
minimum, by not allowing the scan index to exceed 80 % of
the −6 dB minimum effective beam width of the search unit at
any depth in the examination material.)
7.4.11 Scanning—Scan the part in accordance with 7.4.12 at
a speed selected in accordance with 7.4.3.
7.4.11.1 Discontinuities—Note and evaluate in accordance
with 7.4.12 all indications that produce signal amplitudes equal
to or greater than the alarm level at the scanning gain
determined in 7.4.10 after ascertaining that the signals are not
produced by surface conditions or geometry.
7.4.11.2 Back Reflection Monitoring—When required, for
straight beam examinations, where geometry permits, the back
reflection signal or back reflection pattern shall be evaluated at
a sensitivity such that this signal, as received from normal,
sound material on the same or like part is at an amplitude of
between 80 and 90 % of the vertical linearity limit. Any drop
in back reflection signal level below 50 % of the normal value
shall be cause for rejection of the part unless it can be shown
that the reduction is due to a non-parallel back surface or back
surface roughness. If back surface roughness is found to be the
cause, the entire examination item shall be reviewed for
conformance to the requirements of 7.4.1.
7.4.12 Evaluation of Discontinuities—Discontinuities shall
be evaluated at the discontinuity depth by manipulating the
search unit to obtain the maximum response and comparing to
the applicable reference standard (whose metal distance equals
the depth of the discontinuity) and discontinuity level speci-
fied. See Table 1.
7.4.12.1 Evaluation 	of 	Multiple 	Discontinuities—
Discontinuities with maximized indications greater than the
multiple discontinuity indication limits in Table 1 are rejectable
if their positions of maximum response are closer than speci-
fied in Table 1.
7.4.12.2 Evaluation 	of 	Linear 	Discontinuities—
Discontinuities with maximized indications greater than al-
lowed by the linear discontinuity indication limits in Table 1
are rejectable if their lengths are greater than the corresponding
lengths given in the table. Methods for measuring lengths are
given in Annex A4.
7.4.13 Corrosion Protection—Parts shall not be held in
immersion tanks beyond the time required for examination.
After completion of ultrasonic examination, all parts shall be
dried and coated with a corrosion protective material, as
necessary, before they are stacked, nested, or placed in contact
with one another in any way.
7.5 Quality Assurance Provisions:
7.5.1 System Performance—In order to check ultrasonic
system performance characteristics, standardization of systems
with respect to sensitivity in accordance with 7.4.9 shall be
performed prior to and immediately after each examination and
after any changes in instrument settings, or instrument
modules, and at intervals not to exceed four hours during
continuous operation. Standardization time interval may be
increased with proven, documented repeatability of the exami-
nation equipment. If the sensitivity is found to have decreased
more than 10 % between standardization checks, the items
E2375 − 16
14	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 15 ===
examined during the interim shall be re-examined at the correct
sensitivity. If the sensitivity is found to have increased by more
than 10 % between standardization checks the sensitivity shall
be readjusted to the correct value as determined by restandard-
izing in accordance with the applicable parts of 7.4.9 and
7.4.10. However in this case no reexamination of items shall be
required. For the purpose of determining standardization
interval, repetitive examinations of identical parts or material
can be considered to be continuous operation.
7.5.2 Data Records—Data records of all examinations shall
be kept on file in accordance with the contract or order.
Records shall provide for traceability to the specific part or lot
examined and shall include the inspector’s identification and
certification level, the date of the examination, and the reason
of rejection of any rejectable item.
7.5.3 Acceptance Classes—Five ultrasonic classes are de-
fined in Table 1 for governing the acceptability of parts and raw
materials. A contract document shall specify the class as
defined in this practice. When a part requires multiple classes,
a contract document shall indicate the area, or zone, to which
each class is applicable. Any other classes not covered by this
practice shall be specified in the contract, or order, or those
listed in Practice B594 so specified for wrought aluminum
products.
7.5.4 Acceptance Criteria for Parts to be Machined—
Discontinuity indications in excess of the specified ultrasonic
class may be permitted if it is established that such disconti-
nuities will be removed by subsequent machining or trim
operations. In such cases, a record of the ultrasonic examina-
tion results shall be provided on a grid map or C-scan showing
the location and size of indications by discontinuity grade with
respect to a “bench mark” on one corner of the surface from
which the material is scanned. A final ultrasonic examination
shall be performed after machining to assure complete removal
of the discontinuity, unless otherwise specified by the contract-
ing agency.
7.5.5 Rejection—Items with indications exceeding the limits
of the contract requirements (see 5.1) or the written procedure
(see 6.4) as applicable, subject to the provisions of 7.5.4, shall
be rejected.
7.6 Marking:
7.6.1 Wrought Metal—Raw Stock—Each item of raw mate-
rial which has been ultrasonically examined and found to
conform to the requirements of this practice and the acceptance
requirements of the contract or order shall be marked with a
symbol containing a “U” and class, if applicable. The accep-
tance stamp shall provide identification of the operator and the
examination facility. Marking shall be applied in such a
manner and location as to be harmless to the item and to
preclude removal, smearing or obliteration by subsequent
handling.
7.6.2 Parts Machined from Wrought Metal—Parts in process
which have been ultrasonically examined and found to be
acceptable shall be identified by stamping the accompanying
paperwork. When practical, the completed parts or raw mate-
rials shall be identified with a final acceptance stamp which
indicates that all required operations have been completed and
accepted. This stamp shall identify the final acceptance opera-
tor and the examination facility.
7.6.3 Other Identification—Other means of identification,
such as dyeing or tagging, or sign-off of the accompanying
paper work, shall be applied when the construction, finish or
functional requirements preclude the use of stamping or as
specified by the contract.
8. Government Contracts
8.1 Data Requirements—The following Data Item Descrip-
tions (DID’s) must be listed, as applicable, on the Contract
Data Requirements List (DD Form 1423) when this practice is
applied on a contract, in order to obtain the data, except where
DoD FAR Supplement 27.475-1 exempts the requirements for
a DD Form 1423.
Reference
Section
DID
Number
DID
Title
Suggested
Tailoring
5.4 and 6.5.3 	DI-MISC-90653 	Test Report 	Contractor’s Format
8.1.1 The above DID was declared as of this date. The
current issue of DoD 5010.12L, Acquisition Management
Systems and Data Requirements Control List (AMSDL), must
be researched to ensure that only current, cleared DID’s are
cited on the Form 1423.
9. Keywords
9.1 angle beam; contact method; immersion ultrasonic;
longitudinal wave; nondestructive; straight beam; ultrasonic;
ultrasonic examination; ultrasonic technique; ultrasound;
wrought metal products; wrought metals
E2375 − 16
15	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 16 ===
ANNEXES
(Mandatory Information)
A1. ANGLE BEAM EXAMINATION
A1.1 Scope:
A1.1.1 This Annex provides angle beam examination re-
quirements and is a mandatory part of this standard to the
extent that it is specified in this standard or in a contract
document. This annex applies to both longitudinal and shear
wave angle beam examinations. Warning—The use of outer
surface and inner surface notches and the angle beam exami-
nation technique described in this annex represent defects near
these surfaces and do not allow verification of coverage for
mid-way discontinuities.
A1.2 General Requirements:
A1.2.1 Beam Angle—Parts and raw materials may be exam-
ined by either contact or immersion techniques utilizing angle
beam techniques. During examination, the sound beam angle in
the object shall not vary more than 62°.
A1.2.2 Contact Angle Beam Search Units—The exit point
and beam angle of the sound beam shall be established for
contact angle beam search units. Search units with beam angles
varying more than 63° from the manufacturer’s indicated
values shall not be used unless the new angle is verified and
marked on the search unit. The International Institute of
Welding (IIW) type ultrasonic reference block (see 7.3.1.3) or
an appropriate substitute may be used to determine the exit
point and beam angle of angle beam search units. For contact
examination of convex surfaces of 4-in. (101.6-mm) radius or
less, and concave surfaces of 4.0-in. (101.6-mm) radius or less,
a curved shoe or wedge, made to match as closely as possible
the radius of the examination piece, shall be required for
examination.
A1.3 Examination Requirements:
A1.3.1 Ring Forgings—Angle beam examination of ring
forgings shall be performed when specified (see Fig. 7). The
ring forgings may be examined by an immersion or contact
shear wave technique. The reference standard for ring forgings
with an outside to inside diameter (OD/ID) ratio that does not
exceed 2.0 to 1 shall contain two longitudinal (axial) notches
with one on the inside surface and the other on the outside
surface. Use a reference reflector notch in accordance with Fig.
4 based on the applicable examination class of Table 1. The
standard shall meet the applicable requirements of 7.3.
A1.3.1.1 Standardization (For Circumferential Scan)—Scan
until the 1 ⁄2 vee-path notch indication from the inside surface
first appears. Place the indication at the farthest position to the
left on the display. Scan relative to the inside surface notch
until the 3 ⁄2 vee-path indication from this notch reappears along
the horizontal trace. Mark these two positions on the face of the
instrument display. Scan until the notch indication from the
outside surface is produced at maximum amplitude between
these two marks. The amplitude of this notch indication shall
be marked on the instrument display. When the examination
instrument employs distance amplitude controls it is recom-
mended that they be used where possible to equalize these
indication amplitudes at a minimum of 50 % of full screen
height. If this is not possible, or if the instrument is not
equipped with a distance-amplitude correction circuit, a
distance-amplitude curve shall be constructed on the display
with the lowest point at a minimum of 20 % of full screen
height.
A1.3.1.2 Examination Method—The examination shall be
performed with the sound beam directed in both the clockwise
and counterclockwise directions with indexing such that each
pass of the search unit overlaps the previous pass by not less
than 20 % of the effective beam width of the search unit
(7.4.10.8). Reject any forging with an indication greater than or
equal to the reference notch indication.
A1.3.2 Solid Round Bars—Angle beam examination of
solid round bars shall be performed when specified (see Fig. 6).
The refraction angle used shall be no greater than 45° (see Fig.
A1.1). Reference standards shall meet the requirements of 7.3,
using reference reflectors in accordance with Fig. 4 or Fig. 5
that are equivalent to the applicable class of examination in
accordance with Table 1.
A1.3.2.1 Examination Method—Ultrasonic instrument set-
tings shall be such that the indication from the reference
standard is at least 50 % of, but less than 100 % of full screen
height. Indexing shall be such that each pass of the search unit
overlaps the previous pass by not less than 20 % of the
effective beam width of the search unit (see 7.4.10.8). Reject
any bar with an indication greater than or equal to the reference
reflector indication.
A1.3.3 Tubing—Angle beam examination, when specified,
shall be performed as described in Practice E213 and illustrated
in Fig. A1.2. Use an angle beam technique in at least two
circumferential directions and preferably also two axial direc-
tions to examine the tubing. The reference standard shall
contain longitudinal (axial) notches, with one on the outer and
one on the inner surface of the standard. If axial scanning is
required, the reference standard shall also contain two circum-
ferential notches, again with one on the outer surface and one
on the inner surface. The notches shall be in accordance with
Fig. 4 based on the applicable class of examination of Table 1.
The reference standard shall meet the applicable requirements
of 7.3. The longitudinal spacing between the centerline of all
notches should not be less than 2 in. (50.8 mm) unless a smaller
spacing can be shown to produce no interference when used
with the search units to be employed for a specific examina-
tion.
A1.3.3.1 Examination Method—To standardize for exami-
nation adjust the equipment to produce clearly identifiable
indications from both the inner and outer surface notches. The
response from both notches shall be made as equal as possible.
For circumferential scanning this may be accomplished by
E2375 − 16
16	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 17 ===
offset of the search unit (see Fig. A1.2). Use the lesser of the
two responses to establish the rejection level. Ultrasonic
instrument settings shall be such that this standardization
response from the reference standard is at least 50 % of, but
less than 100 % of, full screen height. Indexing shall be such
that each pass of the search unit overlaps the previous pass by
not less than 20 % of the effective beam width of the sound
beam (see 7.4.10.8). All indications that are equal to or greater
than the rejection level established during standardization shall
be cause for rejection.
A1.3.4 Flat Surface Angle Beam Examination—When flat
surface angle beam examination is required use the reference
Block illustrated in Fig. 3 for both immersion and contact
examination.
A1.3.4.1 Coverage—Parts may be examined at refracted
angles of 45 6 5° for a section thickness greater than one inch
and 60 6 5° for a section thickness less than one inch.
A1.3.4.2 Standardization—Standardization of examination
shall be accomplished by determining the distance-amplitude
relationship for the examination as follows:
(1) For parts 0.50 to 1.0 in. thick:
(a) Position the search unit to provide sound entry at
points one, two, three, and four in accordance with Fig. A1.3.
(b) The signal amplitude shall be adjusted to 80% of
vertical limit at whichever position gives the highest amplitude
signal.
(c) Without changing the gain control, the search unit
shall be positioned for maximum response at the other three
positions and the signal amplitudes at all positions shall be
marked on the screen or transparent overlay. The points shall
be joined with a smooth curve. Extrapolation shall be used to
extend the curve to the zero metal travel distance position. Fig.
A1.3 shows a typical angle beam distance amplitude correction
curve.
(d) The search unit shall then be positioned at sound entry
point five for maximum response from the applicable size
flat-bottom hole, and instrument gain shall be adjusted to bring
the peak of the signal to the distance-amplitude correction
curve at points two and five of Fig. A1.3.
(e) If multiple skip distances are to be used, the search
unit shall be placed to provide sound entry at point seven and
maximum amplitude response from the 11 ⁄4 vee path flat-
bottom standardization hole shall be marked on the screen.
This point shall be used to extend the distance amplitude
correction curve.
(f) When the reference standard is thinner than 3 ⁄4 in. and
side-drilled holes are not used, sound entry points five, six, and
seven shall be used to establish the distance amplitude correc-
tion curve.
(g) Alternatively, EDAC may be used to equalize the
responses of DAC position signals at 80 % FSD prior to setting
the sensitivity to bring the applicable flat bottom hole response
to 80 % of the vertical linearity limit.
(2) Setup technique for parts over 1 in. thick:
N OTE 1—The offset distance “D,” from the centerline of the round to the centerline of the search unit, that creates a shear wave no greater than 45°
by:
D $ 0.707R ~VLW/VSM!
where:
D 	= offset distance,
R 	= radius,
VLW 	= velocity of incident longitudinal wave in water, and
VSM 	= velocity of refracted wave in metal.
FIG. A1.1 Angle Beam—Round Bar Examination
E2375 − 16
17	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 18 ===
(a) Position search unit to provide sound entry at points
one, two, three, and four and the additional side-drilled holes in
accordance with Fig. A1.4.
(b) Distance amplitude correction at metal travel distance
between sound entry surface and position one, the 1 ⁄4 T
side-drilled hole, shall be established by reflections from the
additional side-drilled holes as shown in Fig. A1.5, Details “A”
and “B.”
(c) The signal amplitude shall be adjusted to 80 % of
vertical limit at whichever position gives the highest amplitude
signal.
(d) Without changing the gain control, the search unit
shall be positioned for maximum response at the other position
and the signal amplitudes at all positions (one, two, three, and
four) shall be marked on the screen or transparent overlay. The
points shall be joined with a smooth curve. Extrapolation shall
be used to extend the curve to the zero metal travel distance
position.
(e) The search unit shall then be positioned for maximum
response at sound entry point 5 and instrument gain shall be
adjusted to bring the peak of the signal to the distance
amplitude correction curve at points two and five in accordance
with Fig. A1.4 presentation.
(f) If multiple skip distances are to be used, the search
unit shall be placed to provide sound entry at point seven and
maximum amplitude response from the 11 ⁄4 vee path flat-
bottom standardization hole shall be marked on the screen.
This point shall be used to extend the distance amplitude
correction curve.
(g) Alternatively, EDAC may be used to equalize the
responses of DAC position signals at 80 % FSD prior to setting
the sensitivity to bring the applicable flat bottom hole response
to 80 % of the vertical linearity limit.
A1.3.5 Examination Method—Indexing shall be such that
each pass of the search unit overlaps the previous pass by not
less than 20 % of the effective beam width. Compare the
amplitude of the discontinuity indication to the amplitude of
the reference reflector indication. Any part or piece of raw
material containing a discontinuity from which the amplitude is
greater than, or equal to, the reference reflector amplitude shall
be marked for rejection.
N OTE 1—Equations for computing Sin θ and d for the respective setup.
Sin θ 5 VLW
VM Sin φ
d 5 VLW
VM ~Sin φ!R
where:
θ 	5 angle of incident beam
φ 	5 angle of refracted beam
VLW 	5 velocity of longitudinal waves in water
VSM 	5 velocity of wave mode in metal ~shear or longitudinal!
d 	5 distance of search unit center line offset from normal to cylinder outer surface
FIG. A1.2 Angle of Incidence and Beam Offset for Circumferential Angle Beam Examination of Hollow Cylinders
E2375 − 16
18	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 19 ===
FIG. A1.3 Typical Angle Beam Standardization at 60° for Flat Surfaces of Thin Specimens
E2375 − 16
19	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 20 ===
FIG. A1.4 Typical Angle Beam Standardization at 45° for Flat Surfaces of Thick Specimens
E2375 − 16
20	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 21 ===
FIG. A1.5 Angle Beam Standardization for Flat Surfaces of Thick Specimens
E2375 − 16
21	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 22 ===
A2. EXAMINATION REPORTS TECHNICAL REQUIREMENTS
A2.1 Scope—This Annex covers the technical content re-
quirements that shall be included on data records when
required by the contract or order. This Annex is mandatory
only when data item description DI-MISC-80653 is cited on
the DD Form 1423.
A2.2 Applicable Documents—This section is not applicable
to this Annex.
A2.3 Reports :
A2.3.1 Data Records—When required by the contract or
purchase order the data record shall consist of the following:
A2.3.1.1 The minimum content specified for the written
procedure in 7.4.
A2.3.1.2 The information required in 7.5.2.
A3. GAIN CONTROL, ATTENUATOR CALIBRATION, AND LINEARITY CHECK
A3.1 This Annex establishes a procedure and limits for
calibrating Gain Controls and Attenuator Switches and for
checking linearity. Other methods may by used when approved
by the cognizant engineering organization.
A3.2 Gain Control and Attenuator Calibration—The fol-
lowing calibrations shall be made at least annually.
A3.2.1 Controls with linear (Decimal) Calibration—The
following procedure shall be used to establish the accuracy of
gain controls and attenuators with linear (Decimal) calibration
markings over a range of 100:1.
A3.2.1.1 Switch the instrument for through-transmission
examination. Turn the damping, reject and pulse length con-
trols to minimum. Connect a typical straight beam search unit
to the “T” (transmitter) connector on the instrument through a
coaxial “tee” connector. Connect the input of a calibrated
external attenuator to the other leg of the “tee” connector and
the output of the attenuator to the “R” (receiver) connector of
the instrument, across which also connect a shielded terminat-
ing resistor equal in value to the characteristic impedance of
the attenuator. (Refer to Practice E317, Method B, for vertical
linearity examination for a further description of these connec-
tions.) The voltage rating of the attenuator should be checked
against the instrument’s pulser voltage when using a “tee”
connector as described. If necessary, a voltage dropping
network may be added between the search unit and attenuator.
A3.2.1.2 Set the instrument’s gain, or attenuator controls, or
both, to settings that correspond to a sensitivity of between 5
and 10 % of the maximum available from the instrument as
indicated by the calibration markings on the controls. With the
external attenuator set for 20 dB attenuation, adjust the position
of the search unit over the target in any suitable reference block
to which the search unit is coupled, and adjust the position of
any instrument damping, pulse length, or uncalibrated gain
control, or a combination of the three, to obtain a response
from the target of between 80 and 95 % FSD. Record this
amplitude and the gain control setting. These will be referred to
below as the reference gain setting and the reference signal
response.
A3.2.1.3 Switch in an additional 6 dB attenuation for a total
of 26 dB on the external attenuator. Adjust the instruments
calibrated gain, or attenuator controls, or both, to produce a
value equal to twice, +6 dB, the initial reference gain setting in
A3.2.1.2. Record the new gain setting and the amplitude of the
resultant signal response. It shall be within 65 % FSD of the
reference signal response obtained in A3.2.1.2.
A3.2.1.4 Switch in an additional 14 dB for a total of 40 dB
on the external attenuator. Set the instrument’s calibrated gain
/ attenuator controls to a value equal to ten times the reference
gain setting in A3.2.1.2. Record the new gain setting and the
amplitude of the resultant signal response. It shall be within
65 % FSD of the reference signal response obtained in
A3.2.1.2.
A3.2.1.5 Switch in an additional 6 dB for a total of 46 dB on
the external attenuator. Adjust the instrument’s calibrated gain
/ attenuator controls to a value equal to 20 times the reference
gain setting in A3.2.1.2. Record the new gain setting and the
amplitude of the resultant signal response. It shall be within
65 % FSD of the reference signal response obtained in
A3.2.1.2.
A3.2.1.6 Switch in an additional 14 dB for a total of 60 dB
on the external attenuator. Adjust the instrument’s calibrated
gain / attenuator controls to a value equal to 100 times the
reference gain setting in A3.2.1.2. Record the new gain setting
and the amplitude of the resultant signal response. It shall be
within 65 % FSD of the reference signal response obtained in
A3.2.1.2.
A3.2.2 dB Calibrated Gain control and Attenuator Switches
(including Smart Knobs, Menu-Guided Parameter Selection,
and so forth)—The following procedure shall be used to
establish the accuracy of gain controls and attenuators.
A3.2.2.1 Switch the instrument for through-transmission
examination. Turn the damping, reject and pulse length con-
trols to minimum. Connect a typical straight beam search unit
to the “T” connector on the instrument through a coaxial “tee”
connector. Connect the input of a calibrated external attenuator
to the other leg of the “tee” connector and the output of the
attenuator to the “R” connector of the instrument, across which
also connect a shielded terminating resistor equal in value to
the characteristic impedance of the attenuator. (Refer to Prac-
tice E317, Method B for vertical linearity testing for a further
description of these connections.)
E2375 − 16
22	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 23 ===
A3.2.2.2 With the external attenuator set for 20 dB
attenuation, set the instrument’s attenuation / gain controls to
obtain a minimum value which produces a signal of approxi-
mately 90 % FSD from the first back reflection of any suitable
reference block to which the search unit is coupled. Record the
signal amplitude.
A3.2.2.3 Increase the external attenuator by 2 dB and
increase the instrument gain (decrease the attenuation) by 2 dB.
Record the resulting signal amplitude. It shall be within 65 %
FSD of the previous signal.
A3.2.2.4 Repeat A3.2.2.3 as many times as necessary to
cover the range of instrument control settings to the point
where “noise,” lack of additional gain, or internal signal “feed
through” in the instrument renders further external attenuation
ineffective. If separate “coarse” and “fine” attenuator controls
are provided, the 2 dB increments need be applied only once to
check calibration of the “fine” control step settings. Increments
equal to the “coarse” control steps shall be used as in A3.2.2.3
to check calibration of the “coarse” control.
A3.2.2.5 If the limits cannot be met at each step, corrective
action must be taken, and the attenuator calibration check shall
be rerun.
A3.3 Linearity Check—The linearity check of a flaw detec-
tion instrument from input to display (and from input to
recorder output if recording is used as the sole source for
indication evaluation) shall be made using a calibrated external
attenuator. (Refer to Practice E317, Method B, for vertical
linearity testing for a further description of these connections.)
This check shall be made annually (calibration).
A3.3.1 The linearity shall be checked over a range of
response amplitude of at least 15 to 90 % FSD in no less than
five steps. The input to the instrument shall be from a search
unit coupled to a suitable reference block. The input signal
shall be of sufficiently low amplitude as to avoid saturation of
early amplifier stages in the instrument. (A high-order back
surface multiple may be used for this purpose.) To avoid
variable output impedance effects from the external attenuator,
its minimum attenuation shall be not less than 20 dB during
this check.
A3.3.2 Measured deflections (or recorder output indica-
tions) shall be within 65 % FSD of the theoretical values for
the attenuation steps used with an additional allowance for
reading error of up to 61 % FSD. Table A3.1 illustrates typical
steps which may be used and the resulting acceptance limits
when the instrument is adjusted to produce an initial 80 % FSD
response with 21 dB external attenuation.
A4. MEASUREMENT OF LENGTH OF LINEAR INDICATION
A4.1 Scope:
A4.1.1 Introduction—This Annex provides two methods for
determining the length of a linear discontinuity. The first
method A4.1.2 is less accurate than the second method A4.1.4.
The second method accurately measures indications that are
shorter than the effective beam width of the search unit at the
estimated depth of the discontinuity. Also, this method requires
an accurate measurement of the effective beam width at the
discontinuity depth, see A4.1.3.
A4.1.2 Measurement of Discontinuity Length by the “−6 dB
Method”—This method accepts the discontinuity length as
equal to the distance that the search tube is displaced along the
line of the discontinuity between the points where the signal
amplitude has decreased to 50 % of its peak value. That
method yields a larger-than-actual length for discontinuities
that are shorter than the search unit beam width. Although that
error is “safe” in the sense that it will not result in the
acceptance of rejectable discontinuities it can lead to the
rejection of discontinuities of less-than-rejectable length.
A4.1.3 Measurement of Total Effective Beam Width of
Search Unit—For this method to yield accurate results it is
necessary that the total effective beam width of the search unit
be known at the estimated depth of the discontinuity. This shall
be measured by scanning the search unit over the FBH at the
TABLE A3.1 Typical Attenuator Linearity Check Data
External
Attenuator
Theoretical
Amplitude 	Amplitude Limits
(dB) 	(% FSD) 	+5 % FSD 	−5 % FSD
20 	89.76 	95 	84
21 	80.00 	– 	–
22 	71.30 	77 	66
23 	63.55 	69 	58
25 	50.48 	56 	45
27 	40.09 	46 	35
29 	31.85 	37 	26
33 	20.10 	26 	15
37 	12.68 	18 	7
E2375 − 16
23	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---

=== PAGE 24 ===
depth in the reference standard that is nearest the depth of the
discontinuity in the examination material. The effective beam
width shall be taken as the distance along the scan line between
the points at which the signal from the FBH falls to 10 % of its
peak value or into the noise level, whichever is greater. Any
other method which can be shown to be capable of measuring
the effective total beam width of the search unit at the
estimated discontinuity depth in the examination material may
be used.
A4.1.4 Measurement of Discontinuity Length by “−20 dB
Method”—After measurement of the total beam width of the
search unit in accordance with A4.1.3, or other equivalent
method, the search unit shall be scanned along the discontinu-
ity and the distance measured between the points at each end
where the signal from the discontinuity is reduced to 10 % of
its peak value (−20 dB) or just disappears into the noise level,
whichever occurs first. The length of the discontinuity may
then be found by subtracting from this distance the measured
beam width of the search unit.
ASTM International takes no position respecting the validity of any patent rights asserted in connection with any item mentioned
in this standard. Users of this standard are expressly advised that determination of the validity of any such patent rights, and the risk
of infringement of such rights, are entirely their own responsibility.
This standard is subject to revision at any time by the responsible technical committee and must be reviewed every five years and
if not revised, either reapproved or withdrawn. Your comments are invited either for revision of this standard or for additional standards
and should be addressed to ASTM International Headquarters. Your comments will receive careful consideration at a meeting of the
responsible technical committee, which you may attend. If you feel that your comments have not received a fair hearing you should
make your views known to the ASTM Committee on Standards, at the address shown below.
This standard is copyrighted by ASTM International, 100 Barr Harbor Drive, PO Box C700, West Conshohocken, PA 19428-2959,
United States. Individual reprints (single or multiple copies) of this standard may be obtained by contacting ASTM at the above
address or at 610-832-9585 (phone), 610-832-9555 (fax), or service@astm.org (e-mail); or through the ASTM website
(www.astm.org). Permission rights to photocopy the standard may also be secured from the Copyright Clearance Center, 222
Rosewood Drive, Danvers, MA 01923, Tel: (978) 646-2600; http://www.copyright.com/
E2375 − 16
24	Copyright ASTM InternationalProvided by IHS Markit under license with ASTM	Licensee=Israel Aerospace Industries Ltd - Lod, Israel/5943181001, User=YIFRACH,Not for Resale, 10/24/2018 23:56:57 MDT	No reproduction or networking permitted without license from IHS
--``,`,`,,````,,`,,``,`,,`,`,``-`-`,,`,,`,`,,`---
