
=== PAGE 1 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
Non-destructive testing of steel
forgings
Part 3: Ultrasonic testing of ferritic or
martensitic steel forgings
BSI Standards Publication

=== PAGE 2 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016 	BRITISH STANDARD
National foreword
This British Standard is the UK implementation of EN 10228-3:2016.
It supersedes BS EN 10228-3:1998 which is withdrawn.
The UK participation in its preparation was entrusted to Technical
Committee ISE/111, Steel Castings and Forgings.
A list of organizations represented on this committee can be
obtained on request to its secretary.
This publication does not purport to include all the necessary
provisions of a contract. Users are responsible for its correct
application.
© The British Standards Institution 2016.
Published by BSI Standards Limited 2016
ISBN 978 0 580 80531 8
ICS 77.040.20; 77.140.85
Compliance with a British Standard cannot confer immunity from
legal obligations.
This British Standard was published under the authority of the
Standards Policy and Strategy Committee on 30 June 2016.
Amendments/corrigenda issued since publication
Date 	Text affected

=== PAGE 3 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EUROPEAN STANDARD
NORME EUROPÉENNE
EUROPÄISCHE NORM
EN 10228-3
June 2016
ICS 77.040.20; 77.140.85 	Supersedes EN 10228-3:1998
English Version
Non-destructive testing of steel forgings - Part 3:
Ultrasonic testing of ferritic or martensitic steel forgings
Essais non destructifs des pièces forgées en acier -
Partie 3 : Contrôle par ultrasons des pièces forgées en
aciers ferritiques et martensitiques
Zerstörungsfreie Prüfung von Schmiedestücken aus
Stahl - Teil 3: Ultraschallprüfung von Schmiedestücken
aus ferritischem oder martensitischem Stahl
This European Standard was approved by CEN on 3 October 2015.
CEN members are bound to comply with the CEN/CENELEC Internal Regulations which stipulate the conditions for giving this
European Standard the status of a national standard without any alteration. Up-to-date lists and bibliographical references
concerning such national standards may be obtained on application to the CEN-CENELEC Management Centre or to any CEN
member.
This European Standard exists in three official versions (English, French, German). A version in any other language made by
translation under the responsibility of a CEN member into its own language and notified to the CEN-CENELEC Management
Centre has the same status as the official versions.
CEN members are the national standards bodies of Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Croatia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia,
Finland, Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania,
Luxembourg, Malta, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey and
United Kingdom.
EUROPEAN COMMITTEE FOR STANDARDIZATION
C O M I T É E U R O P É E N D E N O R M A L I S A T I O N
E U R O P Ä I S C H E S K O M I T E E F Ü R N O R M U N G
CEN-CENELEC Management Centre: Avenue Marnix 17, B-1000 Brussels
© 2016 CEN 	All rights of exploitation in any form and by any means reserved
worldwide for CEN national Members.
Ref. No. EN 10228-3:2016 E

=== PAGE 4 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
2
Contents 	Page
European foreword....................................................................................................................................................... 4
1 	Scope .................................................................................................................................................................... 5
2 	Normative references .................................................................................................................................... 5
3 	Terms and definitions ................................................................................................................................... 5
4 	Mandatory information ................................................................................................................................ 6
5 	Test procedure ................................................................................................................................................. 6
5.1 	General ................................................................................................................................................................ 6
5.2 	Form ..................................................................................................................................................................... 6
5.3 	Content ................................................................................................................................................................ 7
6 	Personnel qualification ................................................................................................................................. 7
7 	Equipment and accessories ......................................................................................................................... 7
7.1 	Instrument ......................................................................................................................................................... 7
7.2 	Probes.................................................................................................................................................................. 7
7.2.1 	General ................................................................................................................................................................ 7
7.2.2 	Contouring ......................................................................................................................................................... 8
7.2.3 	Nominal frequency ......................................................................................................................................... 8
7.2.4 	Normal-beam probes ..................................................................................................................................... 8
7.2.5 	Angle-beam probes......................................................................................................................................... 8
7.2.6 	Dual-element probes ..................................................................................................................................... 8
7.3 	Calibration blocks ........................................................................................................................................... 8
7.4 	Reference blocks ............................................................................................................................................. 8
7.5 	Couplant.............................................................................................................................................................. 8
8 	Routine calibration and checking ............................................................................................................. 9
9 	Stage of manufacture ..................................................................................................................................... 9
10 	Surface condition ............................................................................................................................................ 9
10.1 	General ................................................................................................................................................................ 9
10.2 	Surface finish related to quality class ...................................................................................................... 9
10.3 	As-forged surface condition ........................................................................................................................ 9
11 	Test sensitivity .............................................................................................................................................. 10
11.1 	General ............................................................................................................................................................. 10
11.2 	Normal-beam probes .................................................................................................................................. 10
11.3 	Angle-beam probes...................................................................................................................................... 10
11.4 	Repeat testing ................................................................................................................................................ 10
12 	Scanning .......................................................................................................................................................... 10
12.1 	General ............................................................................................................................................................. 10
12.2 	Complex forgings .......................................................................................................................................... 11
12.3 	Grid scanning coverage .............................................................................................................................. 11
12.4 	100 % scanning coverage .......................................................................................................................... 11
12.5 	Scanning speed.............................................................................................................................................. 11
13 	Classification .................................................................................................................................................. 14
13.1 	Classification of indications ..................................................................................................................... 14
13.2 	Classification of discontinuities .............................................................................................................. 16

=== PAGE 5 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
3
14 	Recording levels and acceptance criteria ............................................................................................ 18
15 	Sizing ................................................................................................................................................................. 20
16 	Test report ...................................................................................................................................................... 20
Annex A (informative) Maximum testable depth and corresponding beam path range for
circumferential angle beam scans .......................................................................................................... 22
Annex B (informative) Amplitude of indication in dB relative to % DAC .............................................. 23
Annex C (informative) Significant technical changes to the version EN 10228-3:1998 ................... 24

=== PAGE 6 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
4
European foreword
This document (EN 10228-3:2016) has been prepared by Technical Committee ECISS/TC 111 “Steel
castings and forgings”, the secretariat of which is held by AFNOR.
This European Standard shall be given the status of a national standard, either by publication of an
identical text or by endorsement, at the latest by December 2016 and conflicting national standards
shall be withdrawn at the latest by December 2016.
Attention is drawn to the possibility that some of the elements of this document may be the subject of
patent rights. CEN [and/or CENELEC] shall not be held responsible for identifying any or all such patent
rights.
This document supersedes EN 10228-3:1998.
Annex C provides the significant technical changes to the previous version EN 10228-3:1998.
EN 10228 consists of the following parts under the general title Non-destructive testing of steel forgings:
— 	Part 1: Magnetic particle inspection;
— 	Part 2: Penetrant testing;
— 	Part 3: Ultrasonic testing of ferritic or martensitic steel forgings;
— 	Part 4: Ultrasonic testing of austenitic and austenitic-ferritic stainless steel forgings.
According to the CEN-CENELEC Internal Regulations, the national standards organizations of the
following countries are bound to implement this European Standard: Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria,
Croatia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia,
France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Malta,
Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland,
Turkey and the United Kingdom.

=== PAGE 7 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
5
1 	Scope
This European Standard describes techniques to be used for the manual, pulse-echo, ultrasonic testing
of forgings manufactured from ferritic and martensitic steel. Mechanized scanning techniques, such as
immersion testing, may be used but should be agreed between the purchaser and supplier
(see Clause 4).
This part of EN 10228 applies to four types of forgings, classified according to their shape and method
of production. Types 1, 2 and 3 are essentially simple shapes. Type 4 covers complex shapes.
This part of EN 10228 does not apply to:
— 	closed die forgings;
— 	turbine rotor and generator forgings.
Ultrasonic testing of austenitic and austenitic-ferritic stainless steel forgings is the subject of
EN 10228-4.
2 	Normative references
The following documents, in whole or in part, are normatively referenced in this document and are
indispensable for its application. For dated references, only the edition cited applies. For undated
references, the latest edition of the referenced document (including any amendments) applies.
EN 1330-1, Non-destructive testing — Terminology — Part 1: List of general terms
EN 1330-4, Non-destructive testing — Terminology — Part 4: Terms used in ultrasonic testing
EN 12668-1, Non-destructive testing — Characterization and verification of ultrasonic examination
equipment — Part 1: Instruments
EN 12668-2, Non-destructive testing — Characterization and verification of ultrasonic examination
equipment — Part 2: Probes
EN 12668-3, Non-destructive testing — Characterization and verification of ultrasonic examination
equipment — Part 3: Combined equipment
EN ISO 2400, Non-destructive testing — Ultrasonic testing — Specification for calibration block No. 1
(ISO 2400)
EN ISO 9712, Non-destructive testing — Qualification and certification of NDT personnel (ISO 9712)
EN ISO 16811, Non-destructive testing — Ultrasonic testing — Sensitivity and range setting (ISO 16811)
EN 	ISO 16827, 	Non-destructive 	testing — 	Ultrasonic 	testing — 	Characterization 	and 	sizing 	of
discontinuities (ISO 16827)
3 	Terms and definitions
For the purposes of this document, the terms and definitions given in EN 1330-1 and EN 1330-4 apply.

=== PAGE 8 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
6
4 	Mandatory information
The following aspects concerning ultrasonic testing shall be agreed between the purchaser and supplier
at the time of the enquiry or order:
a) 	the manufacturing stage(s) at which ultrasonic testing shall be performed (see Clause 9);
b) 	the volume(s) to be tested and whether grid scanning coverage or 100 % scanning coverage is
required. (see Clause 12);
c) 	the use of dual-element probes for near surface testing (see 7.2.6);
d) 	the quality class required, or the quality classes and the zones to which they apply (see Clause 14);
e) 	the applicable recording/acceptance criteria if different from those detailed in Table 5, Table 6 or
Table 7;
f) 	whether any special scanning coverage, equipment or couplant is required in addition to that
detailed in Clauses 7 and 12;
g) 	the scanning technique to be used if not manual (see Clause 1);
h) 	the sizing techniques to be used for extended discontinuities (see Clause 15);
i) 	the technique(s) to be used for setting sensitivity (see Clause 11);
j) 	whether the test shall be conducted in the presence of the purchaser or his representative;
k) 	whether a written procedure shall be submitted for approval by the purchaser (see Clause 5);
l) 	whether testing by angle-beam probes is required (see 11.3);
m) the remaining test requirements for complex forgings (type 4) (see 12.2).
5 	Test procedure
5.1 General
Ultrasonic testing shall be performed in accordance with a written test procedure. Where specified in
the enquiry or order, the written test procedure shall be submitted to the purchaser for approval prior
to the test.
5.2 Form
This written test procedure shall be one of the following:
a) 	a product specification;
b) 	a procedure written specifically for the application;
c) 	this part of EN 10228 may be used if it is accompanied by testing details specific to the application.

=== PAGE 9 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
7
5.3 Content
The test procedure shall contain the following details as minimum requirements:
a) 	description of the forgings to be tested;
b) 	reference documents;
c) 	qualification of testing personnel;
d) 	stage of manufacture at which the test is carried out;
e) 	surface areas specified in terms of the applicable quality classes;
f) 	preparation of scanning surfaces;
g) 	couplant;
h) 	description of the test equipment;
i) 	calibration and checking of the test equipment;
j) 	scanning plan;
k) 	description and sequence of testing operations;
l) 	recording/evaluation levels;
m) characterization of discontinuities;
n) 	acceptance criteria;
o) 	test report.
6 	Personnel qualification
Personnel shall be qualified in accordance with EN ISO 9712.
7 	Equipment and accessories
7.1 Instrument
The ultrasonic instrument shall feature A-Scan presentation and conform to EN 12668-1.
7.2 Probes
7.2.1 General
Normal-beam probes and angle-beam probes shall conform to the requirements of EN 12668-2.
Where further information is required supplementary probes may also be used. Supplementary probes
shall not be used for the initial detection of discontinuities. It is recommended that supplementary
probes conform to EN 12668-2.

=== PAGE 10 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
8
7.2.2 Contouring
Probes shall be contoured when required by EN ISO 16811.
7.2.3 Nominal frequency
Probes shall have a nominal frequency in the range from 1 MHz to 6 MHz.
7.2.4 Normal-beam probes
Effective transducer diameter shall be in the range from 10 mm to 40 mm.
7.2.5 Angle-beam probes
For the transverse waves, the angle-beam probes shall be in the range from 35° to 70°.
Effective transducer area shall be in the range from 20 mm 2 to 625 mm 2.
7.2.6 Dual-element probes
If near-surface testing is required (see Clause 4), then dual-element probes shall be used.
7.3 Calibration blocks
Calibration blocks shall conform to EN ISO 2400.
7.4 Reference blocks
Reference blocks shall be made available when sensitivity shall be established by the distance-
amplitude curve (DAC) technique and/or when discontinuities shall be sized in terms of amplitude
relative to reference reflectors by the DAC technique. The surface condition of the reference block shall
be representative of the surface condition of the object to be tested. Unless otherwise specified the
reference block shall contain at least three reflectors covering the entire depth range under
examination.
The form of the reference block will depend upon the application. It shall be manufactured from one of
the following:
a) 	an excess length of the object to be tested;
b) 	a part of the same material and with the same heat treatment condition as the object to be tested;
c) 	an object having similar acoustic properties to the object to be tested.
Reference blocks shall not be used for the distance-gain-size (DGS) technique unless it is required to
check the accuracy of a particular DGS diagram.
The sizes of reflectors in the reference block are governed by the sizes detailed in Tables 5 and 6 as
appropriate. Different sizes of reflectors from those detailed in Tables 5 and 6 may be used provided the
test sensitivity is corrected accordingly.
7.5 Couplant
The couplant used shall be appropriate to the application. The same type of couplant shall be used for
the setting of range and sensitivity, for scanning and for the assessment of discontinuities.
NOTE 	Examples of suitable couplants are: water (with or without corrosion inhibitor or softener), grease, oil,
glycerol and water cellulose paste.

=== PAGE 11 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
9
After completion of the test, the couplant shall be removed if its presence could adversely affect later
manufacturing or testing operations or the integrity of the test object.
8 	Routine calibration and checking
The combined equipment (instrument and probes) shall be calibrated and checked in accordance with
the requirements detailed in EN 12668-3.
9 	Stage of manufacture
Ultrasonic testing shall be performed after the final heat treatment unless otherwise agreed at the time
of enquiry or order (see Clause 4), e.g. at the latest possible stage of manufacture for areas of the forging
which are not practicable to test after the final heat treatment.
For both cylindrical and rectangular forgings, which shall be bored, it is recommended to carry out
ultrasonic testing before boring.
10 Surface condition
10.1 General
Scanning surfaces shall be free from paint, non-adhering scale, dry couplant, surface irregularities or
any other substance which could reduce coupling efficiency, hinder the free movement of the probe or
cause errors in interpretation.
10.2 Surface finish related to quality class
The surface finish shall be compatible with the required quality class (see Table 1).
Table 1 — Surface finish related to quality class a
Surface finish
Quality class and roughness Ra
1 	2 	3 	4
≤ 25 μm 	≤ 12,5 μm 	≤ 6,3 μm
Machined 	X 	X 	X
Machined and heat treated 	X 	X 	–
a 	X signifies the quality class that can be achieved for the specified surface finish
10.3 As-forged surface condition
Where forgings are supplied in the as-forged surface condition they shall be considered acceptable
providing the specified quality class can be achieved.
NOTE 	It is difficult to carry out a comprehensive test on as-forged surfaces. Shot blasting, sand blasting or
surface grinding is recommended to ensure that acoustic coupling can be maintained. Normally only quality class
1 is applicable.

=== PAGE 12 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
10
11 Test sensitivity
11.1 General
Test sensitivity shall be sufficient to ensure the detection of the smallest discontinuities required by the
recording/evaluation levels for the particular quality class specified (see Tables 5, 6 and 7).
One of the techniques detailed in 11.2 and 11.3 (DAC or DGS) shall be used to establish sensitivity for
scanning with a particular probe (see Clause 4). The procedure to be used in each case shall be in
accordance with EN ISO 16811.
11.2 Normal-beam probes
For normal-beam probes one of the following techniques shall be used to establish the sensitivity for
scanning:
a) 	Distance-amplitude curve (DAC) technique based upon the use of side-drilled holes (flat-bottomed
holes possible);
b) 	Distance-gain-size (DGS) technique (disc-shaped reflectors).
The procedure to be used in each case shall be in accordance with EN ISO 16811.
11.3 Angle-beam probes
For angle-beam probes one of the following techniques shall be used to establish the sensitivity for
scanning:
a) 	DAC technique using 3 mm diameter side-drilled holes;
b) 	DGS technique (disc-shaped reflectors).
The procedure to be used in each case shall be in accordance with EN ISO 16811.
The DAC and DGS techniques shall not be compared for angle-beam probes.
11.4 Repeat testing
Where repeat testing is performed, the same technique for establishing sensitivity (DAC or DGS) shall
be used as was initially used.
12 Scanning
12.1 General
Scanning shall be performed using the manual contact pulse-echo technique.
The minimum scanning coverage required is dictated by the type of forging and whether grid scanning
coverage or 100 % scanning coverage has been specified in the enquiry or order (see Clause 4).
Table 2 classifies four types of forging according to their shapes and method of production.
Table 3 specifies the requirements for normal-beam scanning coverage for forging types 1, 2 and 3.
Table 4 specifies the requirements for angle-beam scanning coverage for forging types 3a 3b and 3c
which have an outside diameter to inside diameter ratio less than 1,6:1. The effective depth of

=== PAGE 13 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
11
circumferentially oriented angle-beam scans is limited by the beam angle and the forging diameter
(see Annex A).
12.2 Complex forgings
For complex shaped forgings or complex shaped parts of forgings (type 4) and small diameter forgings,
test requirements shall include, as a minimum, the required beam angles, scanning directions and
extent of scanning coverage (grid or 100 %). The remaining test requirements shall be agreed between
purchaser and supplier (see 4 m)).
12.3 Grid scanning coverage
Grid scanning shall be performed with the probe or probes traversed along the grid lines defined in
Tables 3 and 4.
Where recordable indications are revealed by grid scanning, additional scanning shall be performed
around the indications to determine their extent.
12.4 100 % scanning coverage
100 % scanning coverage shall be performed over the surfaces specified in Tables 3 and 4. Consecutive
probe traverses shall overlap by at least 10 % of the effective beam diameter.
12.5 Scanning speed
Manual scanning speed shall not exceed 150 mm/s.

=== PAGE 14 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
12
Table 2 — Classification of forgings according to their shape and method of production
Type 	Shape Usual method of
production a
1ab 	Elongated 	with 	round 	or 	approximately 	round
section, e.g. bars, rods, cylinders, shafts, journals,
discs cut from bars
Direct forged1bb 	Elongated 	with 	rectangular 	or 	approximately
rectangular section, e.g. bars, rods, blocks, sections
cut from bars
2 c , d 	Flattened, e.g. discs, plate, flywheels
Upset
3a 	Hollow cylindrical shapes, e.g. bottles, compressed
gas tanks
Mandrel forged
3b 	Hollow cylindrical shapes, e.g. rings, flanges, rims 	Expanded
3c 	Ring rolling
4 	All forgings or parts of forgings with complex shape 	Various
a 	The purchaser shall be informed of the method of production at the time of enquiry and order.
b 	Type 1 forgings may incorporate bores of small diameter relative to the major dimensions.
c 	Type 2 forgings may eventually be drilled (e.g. binding discs).
d 	Type 2 forgings include products manufactured from forged billets and bars.

=== PAGE 15 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
13
Table 3 — Scanning coverage with normal-beam probes
Type 	Grid Scanninga 	100 % Scanninga, b
1
1a
Diameter, D, (mm) 	Scan linesc
Scan 100 % around
at 	least 	180° 	of
cylindrical surface.
D ≤ 200
200 < D ≤ 500
500 < D ≤ 1000
1000 < D
2 at 90°
3 at 60°
4 at 45°
6 at 30°
1b
Scan along the lines of a square-link
grid on two perpendicular surfaces c, d
Scan 100 % on two
perpendicular
surfaces
2
Scan along the lines of a square-link
grid around 360° on the cylindrical
surface and one lateral surface d
Scan 100 % around
at least 180° on the
cylindrical 	surface
and 100 % of one
lateral surface.
3 	3a
Scan along the lines of a square-link
grid 	around 	360° 	on 	the 	outer
cylindrical surface d
Scan 100 % around
360° on the outer
cylindrical surface.
3b and 3c
Scan along the lines of a square-link
grid 	around 	360° 	on 	the 	outer
cylindrical surface and one lateral
surface d
Scan 100 % around
360° on the outer
cylindrical 	surface
and 	one 	lateral
surface.
4 	Scanning coverage shall be specified in the enquiry or order.
a 	Additional scanning (for example in both axial directions for type 3a) may be carried out if specified in the
enquiry or order.
b 	100 % means at least 10 % beam overlap between consecutive probe traverses.
c 	For types 1a or 1b, if the presence of a bore prevents the opposite surface being reached, the number of scan
lines shall be doubled symmetrically.
d 	The grid line separation shall be equal to the part thickness up to a maximum of 200 mm.

=== PAGE 16 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
14
Table 4 — Scanning coverage with angle-beam probes
Type 	Grid scanninga 	100 % Scanninga, b
3c 	3a
3b
Scan in both directions
along 360° circumferential
grid lines, the separation of
which is equal to the radial
thickness up to a maximum
of 200 mm.
Scan in both
circumferential
directions over 100 %
on the outer cylindrical
surface.
4 	Scanning coverage shall be agreed at time of enquiry or order
a 	Additional scanning coverage may be carried out if specified in the enquiry or order.
b 	100 % means at least 10 % beam overlap between consecutive probe traverses.
c 	For type 3c this test procedure is normally not used but it may be agreed at time of enquiry.
13 Classification
13.1 Classification of indications
Indications shall be classified according to their echodynamic patterns.
a) 	Pattern 1:
As the probe is moved, the A-scan display shows a single sharp indication rising smoothly in
amplitude to a maximum and then falling smoothly to zero (see Figure 1).
This pattern corresponds to discontinuity dimensions smaller than or equal to the −6 dB beam
profile, such as the echodynamic pattern obtained from the side-drilled holes used to plot the beam
profile.

=== PAGE 17 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
15
a) A-scan presentation 	b) Echodynamic pattern
Key
a) 	X 	pattern of A-Scan at fixed probe position (at typical probe position)
b) 	X 	pattern of curve amplitude against probe shift (variation in signal amplitude as probe is moved)
Y 	amplitude
Figure 1 — Pattern 1 - A-scan presentation and echo envelope presentation
b) 	Pattern 2:
As the probe is moved, the A-scan display shows a single sharp indication rising smoothly in
amplitude to a maximum which is maintained with or without amplitude variation, and then falling
smoothly to zero (see Figure 2). This pattern corresponds to discontinuity dimensions greater than
the −6 dB beam profile.
a) A-scan presentation 	b) Echodynamic pattern
Key
a) 	X 	pattern of A-Scan at fixed probe position (at typical probe position)
b) 	X 	pattern of curve amplitude against probe shift (variation in signal amplitude as probe is moved)
Y 	amplitude
Figure 2 — Pattern 2 - A-scan presentation and echo envelope presentation

=== PAGE 18 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
16
13.2 Classification of discontinuities
Discontinuities shall be classified according to their echodynamic patterns as follows:
a) 	Point-like discontinuity:
Echodynamic pattern 1 and/or dimension equal to or less than the - 6 dB beam width (see
Figure 3).
b) 	Extended discontinuity:
Echodynamic pattern 2 and/or dimensions greater than the - 6 dB beam width (see Figure 4).
c) 	Isolated discontinuities:
The distance d, between points corresponding to the maxima of the indications of adjacent
discontinuities exceeds 40 mm (see Figure 5).
d) 	Grouped discontinuities:
The distance d, between points corresponding to the maxima of the indications of adjacent
discontinuities is less than or equal to 40 mm (see Figure 6).
Key
1 	conventional outline of −6 dB discontinuity
Dp 	width of beam at depth of discontinuity
L 	conventional length of −6 dB discontinuity
Figure 3 — Point-like discontinuity
(L ≤ Dp )

=== PAGE 19 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
17
Key
1 	conventional outline of −6 dB discontinuity
Dp 	width of beam at depth of discontinuity
L 	conventional length of −6 dB discontinuity
Figure 4 — Extended discontinuity
(L > Dp )
Key
1 	conventional outline of −6 dB discontinuity
Dp 	width of beam at depth of discontinuity
d 	distance between two discontinuities
L 	conventional length of −6 dB discontinuity
Figure 5 — Isolated discontinuities
(L ≤ Dp , d > 40 mm)

=== PAGE 20 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
18
Key
1 	conventional outline of −6 dB discontinuity
Dp 	width of beam at depth of discontinuity
d 	distance between two discontinuities
L 	conventional length of −6 dB discontinuity
Figure 6 — Grouped discontinuities
(L ≤ Dp , d ≤ 40 mm)
14 Recording levels and acceptance criteria
The applicable quality class(es) shall be agreed between the purchaser and supplier (see Clause 4).
Tables 5, 6 and 7 detail recording levels and acceptance criteria which shall be applied to four quality
classes.
Several quality classes may be applied to a forging or to parts of a forging; Quality class 4 is the most
stringent, dictating the lowest recording levels and most stringent acceptance criteria. Where agreed,
recording/evaluation levels and acceptance criteria different from those detailed in Tables 5, 6 and 7
may be used.

=== PAGE 21 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
19
Table 5 — Quality classes, recording levels and acceptance criteria for normal-beam probes
Parameter Quality class
1 	2 	3 	4
Recording level
Equivalent flat-bottomed holes (EFBH) deq mma > 8 	> 5 	> 3 	> 2
Ratio R for rapid backwall echo reductionb, c 	≤ 0,1 	≤ 0,3 	≤ 0,5 	≤ 0,6
Acceptance criteria
EFBH (isolated discontinuities) deq mma ≤ 12 	≤ 8 	≤ 5 	≤ 3
EFBH (extended or grouped discontinuities) deq mma 	≤ 8 	≤ 5 	≤ 3 	≤ 2
a 	deq = Diameter of equivalent flat-bottomed hole.
b 	n
o,n
F
R F
=
where:
n = 1 for t ≥ 60 mm
n = 2 for t < 60 mm
Fn = amplitude (screen height) of the n th reduced backwall echo
Fo,n = amplitude (screen height) of the n th backwall echo in the nearest discontinuity-free area at the same range
as Fn .
c 	If the reduction in backwall echo exceeds the recording level, this shall be further investigated. Ratio R
applies only to rapid reduction of backwall echo caused by the presence of a discontinuity.
Table 6 — Quality classes, recording levels and acceptance criteria for angle beam probes using
DGS technique with flat-bottomed holes
Quality class 	1a 	2 	3 	4
Recording level deq mmb 	– 	> 5 	> 3 	> 2
Acceptance criteria for isolated discontinuities deq mmb 	– 	≤ 8 	≤ 5 	≤ 3
Acceptance criteria for extended or grouped discontinuities deq mmb 	– 	≤ 5 	≤ 3 	≤ 2
a 	Angle beam scanning does not apply to quality class 1.
b 	deq = Diameter of equivalent flat-bottomed hole.

=== PAGE 22 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
20
Table 7 — Quality classes, recording levels and acceptance criteria for angle beam probes using
DAC technique a
Quality class
Nominal test
frequency c
MHz
Recording
level
%
(DAC)
Acceptance criteria
Isolated
discontinuitiesa,d
%
(DAC)
Extended or grouped
discontinuities a, d
%
(DAC)
1 b 	- 	- 	- 	-
2 	1 	50 	100 	50
2 	100 	200 	100
3 	2 	50 	100 	50
4 	100 	200 	100
4 	2 	30 	60 	30
4 	50 	100 	50
a 	Based on 3 mm diameter side-drilled holes.
b 	Angle beam scanning does not apply to Quality class 1.
c 	A DAC based on 3 mm diameter side-drilled holes shall be constructed for each frequency and each probe.
d 	The indication amplitude in dB relative to the DAC is given in Annex B.
15 Sizing
Where the extent of a discontinuity is required to be evaluated, one or more of the following techniques,
as agreed between the purchaser and the supplier, shall be used. These techniques shall be carried out
in accordance with the requirements detailed in EN ISO 16827:
a) 	6 dB-drop technique;
b) 	20 dB-drop technique;
c) 	maximum amplitude technique.
16 Test report
All tests shall be the subject of a written report which shall include the following information as
minimum requirements:
a) 	name of supplier;
b) 	order number;
c) 	identification of forging(s) to be tested;
d) 	scope of the test: testing zones and applicable quality classes;

=== PAGE 23 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
21
e) 	stage of manufacture at which ultrasonic testing was performed;
f) 	surface condition;
g) 	equipment used (instrument, probes, calibration and reference blocks);
h) 	technique(s) used to set test sensitivity;
i) 	reference to this standard and, if applicable, reference to the written procedure used;
j) 	test results: location, classification and amplitude (in terms of FBH-equivalent diameter, or in
percent of SDH) of all discontinuities exceeding the appropriate recording level;
k) 	details of any restrictions to the required scanning coverage and if applicable the extent of the
(untested) near surface zone;
l) 	date of the test;
m) name, qualification, certification (if specified) and signature of the operator.

=== PAGE 24 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
22
Annex A
(informative)
Maximum testable depth and corresponding beam path range for
circumferential angle beam scans
Figure A.1 and Table A.1 show the maximum testable depth M for circumferential angle beam scans for
a given probe and beam path range D.
Key
1 	reflector
D 	is the beam path range for normal incidence on a radial reflector
M 	is the maximum testable depth for a particular probe angle and outside radius R
R 	outside radius
X 	beam angle
Regarding X, M and D, see Table A.1 underneath.
Figure A.1 — Maximum testable depth and corresponding beam path range for circumferential
angle beam scans
Table A.1 — Maximum testable depth and corresponding beam path range
Beam Angle, X Maximum Testable Depth,
M Beam Path Range, D
70° 	0,06R 	0,34R
60° 	0,13R 	0,50R
50° 	0,24R 	0,64R
45° 	0,30R 	0,70R
35° 	0,42R 	0,82R
NOTE 	The maximum testable depth and beam path range to this depth for radial reflectors are
given in terms of the outside radius R of the forging.

=== PAGE 25 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
23
Annex B
(informative)
Amplitude of indication in dB relative to % DAC
As an alternative to constructing a DAC which is a percentage of the 3 mm diameter side-drilled hole
DAC (100 % DAC), the required recording/acceptance level may be achieved by constructing the 3 mm
DAC (100 % DAC) and adjusting the amplitude according to Table B.1.
Table B.1 — Amplitude of indication in dB relative to % DAC
DAC
%
Amplitude of indication relative to DAC
dB
30 	– 10
50 	– 6
60 	– 4
100 	0
200 	+ 6

=== PAGE 26 ===
BS EN 10228-3:2016
EN 10228-3:2016 (E)
24
Annex C
(informative)
Significant technical changes to the version EN 10228-3:1998
Some significant technical changes to the previous version EN 10228-3:1998 are listed below:
a) 	updating of the normative references;
b) 	generally updating and alignment of the designations to the actual state of art;
c) 	new Table 1 concerning surface finish related to quality class;
d) 	updating of method of production for the types 3b and 3c in Table 2;
e) 	supplementary footnote c) in Table 4 concerning scanning coverage with angle beam probes for
products of type 3c);
f) 	correlation between terms and Figures 1 and 2 have been updated in Clause 13;
g) 	Note in the table in Annex A updated.

=== PAGE 27 ===
This page deliberately left blank

=== PAGE 28 ===
BSI is the national body responsible for preparing British Standards and other
standards-related publications, information and services.
BSI is incorporated by Royal Charter. British Standards and other standardization
products are published by BSI Standards Limited.
British Standards Institution (BSI)
About us
We bring together business, industry, government, consumers, innovators
and others to shape their combined experience and expertise into standards
-based solutions.
The knowledge embodied in our standards has been carefully assembled in
a dependable format and refined through our open consultation process.
Organizations of all sizes and across all sectors choose standards to help
them achieve their goals.
Information on standards
We can provide you with the knowledge that your organization needs
to succeed. Find out more about British Standards by visiting our website at
bsigroup.com/standards or contacting our Customer Services team or
Knowledge Centre.
Buying standards
You can buy and download PDF versions of BSI publications, including British
and adopted European and international standards, through our website at
bsigroup.com/shop, where hard copies can also be purchased.
If you need international and foreign standards from other Standards Development
Organizations, hard copies can be ordered from our Customer Services team.
Copyright in BSI publications
All the content in BSI publications, including British Standards, is the property
of and copyrighted by BSI or some person or entity that owns copyright in the
information used (such as the international standardization bodies) and has
formally licensed such information to BSI for commercial publication and use.
Save for the provisions below, you may not transfer, share or disseminate any
portion of the standard to any other person. You may not adapt, distribute,
commercially exploit, or publicly display the standard or any portion thereof in any
manner whatsoever without BSI’s prior written consent.
Storing and using standards
Standards purchased in soft copy format:
• A British Standard purchased in soft copy format is licensed to a sole named
user for personal or internal company use only.
• The standard may be stored on more than 1 device provided that it is accessible
by the sole named user only and that only 1 copy is accessed at any one time.
• A single paper copy may be printed for personal or internal company use only.
Standards purchased in hard copy format:
• A British Standard purchased in hard copy format is for personal or internal
company use only.
• It may not be further reproduced – in any format – to create an additional copy.
This includes scanning of the document.
If you need more than 1 copy of the document, or if you wish to share the
document on an internal network, you can save money by choosing a subscription
product (see ‘Subscriptions’).
Reproducing extracts
For permission to reproduce content from BSI publications contact the BSI
Copyright & Licensing team.
Subscriptions
Our range of subscription services are designed to make using standards
easier for you. For further information on our subscription products go to
bsigroup.com/subscriptions.
With British Standards Online (BSOL) you’ll have instant access to over 55,000
British and adopted European and international standards from your desktop.
It’s available 24/7 and is refreshed daily so you’ll always be up to date.
You can keep in touch with standards developments and receive substantial
discounts on the purchase price of standards, both in single copy and subscription
format, by becoming a BSI Subscribing Member.
PLUS is an updating service exclusive to BSI Subscribing Members. You will
automatically receive the latest hard copy of your standards when they’re
revised or replaced.
To find out more about becoming a BSI Subscribing Member and the benefits
of membership, please visit bsigroup.com/shop.
With a Multi-User Network Licence (MUNL) you are able to host standards
publications on your intranet. Licences can cover as few or as many users as you
wish. With updates supplied as soon as they’re available, you can be sure your
documentation is current. For further information, email subscriptions@bsigroup.com.
Revisions
Our British Standards and other publications are updated by amendment or revision.
We continually improve the quality of our products and services to benefit your
business. If you find an inaccuracy or ambiguity within a British Standard or other
BSI publication please inform the Knowledge Centre.
Useful Contacts
Customer Services
Tel: +44 345 086 9001
Email (orders): orders@bsigroup.com
Email (enquiries): cservices@bsigroup.com
Subscriptions
Tel: +44 345 086 9001
Email: subscriptions@bsigroup.com
Knowledge Centre
Tel: +44 20 8996 7004
Email: knowledgecentre@bsigroup.com
Copyright & Licensing
Tel: +44 20 8996 7070
Email: copyright@bsigroup.com
NO COPYING WITHOUT BSI PERMISSION EXCEPT AS PERMITTED BY COPYRIGHT LAW
BSI Group Headquarters
389 Chiswick High Road London W4 4AL UK
