
=== PAGE 1 ===
V2500 First Stage High Pressure Turbine Disks
Off-Wing Immersion Ultrasonic Inspection for Crack Detection
NDIP-1226 Rev F
WARNING
THIS DOCUMENT MAY CONTAIN INFORMATION SUBJECT TO THE INTERNATIONAL TRAFFIC IN ARMS REGULATION (ITAR) OR THE
EXPORT ADMINISTRATION REGULATION (EAR) OF 1979. THIS INFORMATION MAY NOT BE EXPORTED, RELEASED, OR
DISCLOSED TO FOREIGN NATIONALS OUTSIDE THE UNITED STATES WITHOUT FIRST COMPLYING WITH THE EXPORT LICENSE
REQUIREMENTS OF THE INTERNATIONAL TRAFFIC IN ARMS REGULATION (ITAR) AND/OR THE EXPORT ADMINISTRATION
REGULATION (EAR). A VIOLATION OF THE ITAR OR EAR MAY BE SUBJECT TO A PENALTY OF UP TO 10 YEARS IMPRISONMENT
AND A FINE OF $1,000,000 UNDER 22 U.S.C 2778 OR SECTION 2410 OF THE EXPORT ADMINISTRATION ACT OF 1979. INCLUDE
THIS NOTICE WITH ANY REPRODUCED PORTION OF THIS DOCUMENT.
RESTRICTION
PAGES OF THIS DOCUMENT MARKED WITH THE NOTICES SET FORTH BELOW CONTAIN CONTRACTOR COMPETITION SENSITIVE
DATA AND/OR PRATT & WHITNEY PROPRIETARY DATA WHICH IS SUBMITTED IN CONFIDENCE. NO DISCLOSURE OR USE OF THIS
INFORMATION IS PERMISSIBLE WITHOUT PRIOR WRITTEN CONSENT OF RAYTHEON TECHNOLOGIES CORPORATION EXCEPT
FOR OFFICIAL PURPOSES WITHIN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.
DOCUMENT PROPERTY RIGHTS NOTICE
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF RAYTHEON TECHNOLOGIES CORPORATION (RTX). YOU MAY NOT POSSESS, USE, COPY
OR DISCLOSE THIS DOCUMENT OR ANY INFORMATION IN IT, FOR ANY PURPOSE, INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION TO DESIGN,
MANUFACTURE OR REPAIR PARTS, OR OBTAIN FAA OR OTHER GOVERNMENT APPROVAL TO DO SO, WITHOUT RTX’S EXPRESS
WRITTEN PERMISSION. NEITHER RECEIPT NOR POSSESSION OF THIS DOCUMENT ALONE, FROM ANY SOURCE, CONSTITUTES
SUCH PERMISSION. POSSESSION, USE, COPYRIGHT OR DISCLOSURE BY ANYONE WITHOUT RTX’S EXPRESS WRITTEN
PERMISSION IS NOT AUTHORIZED AND MAY RESULT IN CRIMINAL AND OR CIVIL LIABILITY.
NOTICES
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information
US Export Controlled: EAR99

=== PAGE 2 ===
September 2021
V2500 First Stage High Pressure Turbine Disks
Off-Wing Immersion Ultrasonic Inspection for Crack
Detection
Instructions described within this procedure do not replace, amend or supersede any
instructions included in other Pratt & Whitney technical publications. Active Service
Bulletins and other technical publications published by Pratt & Whitney comprise
approved technical data.
Written By: Dave Raulerson, Bill Brown
Approved By: Kevin Smith
Original Issue Date: 23-December, 2020

=== PAGE 3 ===
September 2021
Revision History:
Revision
Letter Revision Date Changes Revision By Approved By
Initial
Release 23-Dec, 2020 N/A D. Raulerson,
B. Brown K. Smith PL4
A 20-Mar, 2021
Correct typos, inspection angle
clarification, disk cleaning,
reporting requirements, revised
noise description (7.8.5) and TOF
rejection criteria (8.1.3)
D. Raulerson,
B. Brown D. Raulerson PL4
B 21-Mar, 2021
Corrected typos, revised equipment
setup section (4.0), clarified
calibration procedure regarding
incident angle (5.1.1) and added
5.1.4, updated section 6.0,
removed incident angle reference
in 7.7.1, revised procedure (7.7 &
7.8), revised TOF criteria (8.1.3) ,
revised sections 9.1.7.21-23.
D. Raulerson,
A. Harmon D. Raulerson PL4
C 8-Jul, 2021
Added collimator and damping
device options;
Modified Marking Pencil details;
Cal block holder is optional;
Revise training requirement;
Added post-calibration requirement
and specifications;
Added surface normalization
requirement;
Added baseline noise requirements
B. Brown,
A. Harmon D. Raulerson PL4
D 4-Aug, 2021
Added interface signal evaluation
requirements to reject criteria
(8.1.4)
Added water contamination/debris
evaluation requirement to reject
criteria (8.1.5)
Updated image in Appendix A to
reflect current reject criteria
A. Harmon,
A. Swope D. Raulerson PL4
E 6-Aug, 2021
Updated formatting in 9.0
Reporting
Updated phrasing associated with
8.1.4.1-8.1.4.3
A. Harmon D. Raulerson PL4
F 2-Sept, 2021
Updated Rejection Criteria to
address C-Scans with average
noise below 5%FSH (8.1.3.3.2)
A. Harmon D. Raulerson PL4

=== PAGE 4 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
1
Table of Contents
1. GENERAL INFORMATION .................................................................................................. 2
2. REQUIRED EQUIMENT ....................................................................................................... 3
3. INSPECTION QUALIFICATIONS ............................................................................................. 5
4. GENERAL EQUIPMENT SETUP .............................................................................................. 6
5. CALIBRATION .................................................................................................................. 7
6. DISK PREPARATION .........................................................................................................10
7. INSPECTION PROCEDURE ..................................................................................................11
8. REJECTION CRITERA .........................................................................................................14
9. REPORTING....................................................................................................................17
10. APPENDIX A: REJECTABLE INDICATION REPORTING .................................................................19

=== PAGE 5 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
2
1.0 General Information
1.1 Scope
1.1.1 The objective of this immersion ultrasonic inspection is to detect radial/axial
cracks in the bore area of 1st stage high pressure turbine (HPT) disks
manufactured from powdered nickel metal. The inspection is conducted on
disks in the finished shape, disassembled condition, with the following part
number(s):
1.1.1.1 PN 2A5001
1.2 This procedure describes the specific information for the V2500 engine model and
details the individual scan plans.
1.3 The inspection is accomplished by applying several scans to the bore are a of the disk.
Scans are designed based on the bore geometry and include one positive 45-degree and
one negative 45-degree circumferential shear inspection.
1.4 The development of calibration and inspection scan plans requires an inspector with a
Level III or equivalent experience, who is familiar with the computer controlled
immersion ultrasonic inspection system used, and is trained in the specific tasks of this
inspection.
1.5 The application of the inspection requires an inspector with a Level II or equivalent
experience, who is familiar with the computer controlled immersion ultrasonic
inspection system used, and is trained in the specific tasks of this inspection.
1.6 Before testing can begin scan plans must be programmed for each part, with approval
from Pratt & Whitney MPE-NDE.
1.7 Before inspection can begin, inspectors must achieve an acceptable score of the POD
qualification testing as administered by Pratt & Whitney MPE-NDE. Only qualified
operators, specifically designated, trained, and approved can perform this inspection. A
Pratt & Whitney task specific certificate will be issued to qualified inspectors.
1.8 The use of collimating and/or damping devices requires approval from Pratt & Whitney
MPE-NDE department. Such a device may be required to address structured noise
associated with side lobes.

=== PAGE 6 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
3
2.0 Required Equipment
2.1 Calibration Blocks
2.1.1 IAE2P16675 - The Angle Calibration Block consists of No. 1 flat bottom holes at
various depths incorporated into a 45-degree angle side. No. 1 flat bottom
holes are machined representing a specific depth from the sound entry surface
2.1.2 The calibration blocks shall be sourced from Pratt & Whitney MPE-NDE
2.2 Calibration Block Holder, optional
2.2.1 IAE2P16674 – 45-degree Calibration Block Holder
2.3 Immersion Ultrasonic Inspection System, consisting of the following or equivalent, available
from:
2.3.1 Inspection Research & Technologies Ltd
2.3.1.1 Ex: LS-200 Immersion Tank and Ultrasonic Scanner
2.3.2 Matec
2.3.2.1 Ex: Model IMT3007-SS-TT-L-ARN or equivalent
Note: This inspection requires a computer-controlled scanning system with C-Scan and digital
data recording. The equipment listed meets the requirements but is not intended to prevent
the use of alternate equivalent scanning systems.
NOTE: THE USE OF ALTERNATE EQUIVALENT SCANNING SYSTEMS MUST BE APPROVED BY
PRATT & WHITNEY MPE-NDE.
2.4 Immersion Ultrasonic Transducers
2.4.1 IAE2P16679 - 5 MHz, 8" Focus, medium bandwidth
2.4.2 Transducers to be sourced through Pratt & Whitney NDE:
gppwmpendetoolsup@prattwhitney.com
2.5 Immersion Ultrasonic Transducer Mirrors
2.5.1 IAE2P16678 - 45-degree 5” length, for 5MHz 8” focus
2.6 Chuck Riser, turn table

=== PAGE 7 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
4
2.6.1 The chuck riser is used to allow centering of the various size diameter disks
2.7 Marking Pencil, PMC-4059
2.8 Optional - IAE1P16217 and IAE1P16014 Handling Tools, Stage 1 HPT disk configurations.
2.9 Optional - IAE1P16221 and IAE1P16366 Handling Tools, Stage 2 HPT disk configurations.
CAUTION: METAL TO METAL CONTACT MUST BE AVOIDED WITH THE HPT DISKS

=== PAGE 8 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
5
3.0 Inspection Qualifications
3.1 Airlines or overhaul facility immersion ultrasonic systems used to conduct this
inspection must be source approved by Pratt & Whitney MPE-NDE. Acceptable POD
performance is required for any systems used for this NDIP.
3.1.1 Interim Testing/Qualification Asset(s) may be provided by MPE-NDE until POD
assets are available.
3.1.2 Once available, POD assets must be used to requalify inspectors.
3.2 Only qualified and approved operators can perform this inspection. A Pratt & Whitney
task specific certificate will be issued to qualified inspectors who successfully complete
the POD process.
3.3 Inspection personnel performing the immersion ultrasonic inspection must meet the
following requirements:
3.3.1 Inspector must have Level II or equivalent training in ultrasonic inspection
3.3.2 Inspector must have demonstrated proficiency in operation of the computer
controlled immersion ultrasonic inspection system
3.3.3 Familiarization with inspection method to be provided by local Level 3.
3.3.4 Inspector must pass POD, or Interim, qualification administered by Pratt &
Whitney MPE-NDE based on successful completion and accurate quantification
of known defects in the PW-approved test part(s). This evaluation is conducted
by Pratt & Whitney approved proctors only. The proctor may advise
inefficiencies as needed to a candidate. Retesting is limited to a single repeat.
3.3.5 Inspector recertification is required if more than six months elapses without
having performed an inspection.
3.3.6 Contact the Pratt and Whitney MPE/NDE for questions regarding POD
qualification and/or Interim testing/qualification.

=== PAGE 9 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
6
4.0 General Equipment Setup
4.1 This NDIP is written with the assumption the inspector is familiar with the operation of
the ultrasonic inspection scanning system and analysis tools.
4.2 Move manipulator to a safe position.
4.3 Home the system.
4.3.1 Select and attach the transducer to the manipulator.
4.3.2 Lower the transducer/manipulator into the water.
4.3.3 Check for air bubbles.
4.3.3.1 Remove any air bubbles with the transducer immersed in the water.
4.3.3.2 Check for air bubbles on the part surfaces such as under the web.
Remove any air bubbles from the part surfaces.
4.4 Place the Angled Calibration Block sensitivity setting standard in the tank.
4.4.1 Check for air bubbles on the ultrasound entry surfaces of the standard.

=== PAGE 10 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
7
5.0 Calibration
5.1 Conduct the calibration procedure to ensure an amplitude of 80 percent vertical screen
height is obtained from each No. 1 FBH in the standard.
5.1.1 Perform calibration.
5.1.1.1 Normalize the transducer to the top surface of the calibration
standard.
5.1.1.2 Set the water path (8-inches).
5.1.1.3 Tilt the transducer to required incidence angle (approximately 18.6
degrees).
5.1.1.3.1 Incident angle may vary depending on environmental
factors. The ultrasonic level III shall identify the
appropriate incident angle sufficient to achieve a 45-
degree refracted shear wave in the part.
5.1.1.4 Adjust water path to 8-inches after transducer angulation.
5.1.1.5 Normalize the A and B axes to maximize the amplitude from the back
surface (45-degree surface) of the calibration standard.
5.1.1.6 Scan transducer while maintaining transducer angulation and water
path.
5.1.1.7 Maximize amplitude from each FBH target, Figure 1.
5.1.1.7.1 Holes L through S, omitting hole J & hole K.

=== PAGE 11 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
8
Figure 1 – Calibration standard
5.1.2 Distance-Amplitude-Correction (DAC)
5.1.2.1 Establish DAC such that all holes used during calibration in section.
5.1.1 achieve 80 percent Full Screen Height.
5.1.3 Curvature Correction
5.1.3.1 Curvature Correction will be required, value(s) are supplied by Pratt
& Whitney specific to each transducer and system.
5.1.3.2 Add Curvature Correction gain to each of the DAC points.
5.1.4 Calibration standard specific gain offsets.
5.1.4.1 Calibration standards have been referenced to a master calibration
standard and gain offsets are provided on the calibration card.
5.1.4.2 Add calibration standard specific gains to each of the DAC points.
5.1.5 Post-Calibration
5.1.5.1 Post-calibration is performed by returning to the calibration block
and verifying the amplitude response of every utilized DAC point.
Acceptable amplitude variance is within +/- 1 dB of initial calibration
amplitude.

=== PAGE 12 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
9
5.1.5.1.1 Post-calibrations exceeding this tolerance will require
all surfaces that yielded rejectable indications since
last successful calibration/post-calibration to be re-
scanned.
5.1.5.1.2 Post-calibrations falling below this tolerance will
require all surfaces since last successful
calibration/post-calibration to be re-scanned.
5.1.5.2 Calibration and post-calibrations must be documented and reported
to Pratt & Whitney via MFT upon completion of data
collection/evaluation.
5.1.5.2.1 Calibration and post-calibrations, and other required
information, must be recorded in Pratt & Whitney
provided template, or approved equivalent
document.
5.1.5.3 Post-calibration is required:
5.1.5.3.1 Prior to shift change.
5.1.5.3.2 Prior to part number change.
5.1.5.3.3 Prior to transducer change.
5.1.5.3.4 Immediately following any event that caused an
unexpected interruption to part scanning/data
evaluation. Such an example would include
unexpected power outage.
5.2 Calibration blocks are to be recertified at Pratt & Whitney NDE on a yearly basis.

=== PAGE 13 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
10
6.0 Disk Preparation
6.1 The disk to be inspected shall be clean and free of any fore ign material or marking which
interfere with the ultrasound penetration & reflection or obscure indications.
6.2 Mark a “start” inspection position (12 o’clock or 0 degrees) on the HPT disk.
6.2.1 Locate the Serial Number (S/N).
6.2.1.1 The S/N is typically located on the rear surface of a blade attachment
tang, adjacent to the tangs with the part number (P/N) and the heat
code (H/C).
6.2.1.2 If “S/N” is on one blade attachment tang and the serial number is on
an adjacent tang, use the blade attachment tang with the “S/N”.
6.2.2 Mark a “start” inspection position on the front and rear surface of the blade
attachment tang with the S/N using an approved marking pencil.
6.3 Record the P/N, S/N, and H/C on the Inspection Sheet.
6.4 Install the disk.
6.5 Set the 12 o’clock position of the disk on the inspection system turntable at 0.0-degree
position.
6.6 Check for, and remove, air bubbles on any surfaces of the volume to be inspected.

=== PAGE 14 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
11
7.0 Inspection Procedure
7.1 Inspect the bore area of the HPT disk for the surfaces identified in Figure 2.
7.1.1 Circumferential shear wave ±45-degree refracted angle.
7.1.2 For Bore ID surface inspection, if Bore offset method is used to generate ±45-
degree refracted angle, use an offset equal to approximately 0.943” (for nominal
radius of 2.910”).
7.1.3 Minimal 2.6” radial volumetric coverage is required, see Figure 2.
Figure 2 V2500 Stage 1 HPT disk - P/N 2A5001, immersion ultrasonic inspection scan plan
7.2 The maximum scan increment for all modes of inspection shall be 0.020 inches.
7.3 The maximum index increment for all modes of inspection shall be 0.020 inch per
revolution.
7.4 The gate threshold for this inspection is set to a minimum amplitude to allow all
inspection data to be collected.

=== PAGE 15 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
12
7.5 Verify water path is set to 8-inches.
7.6 Verify mirror is fully seated on the transducer
7.7 Normalize on the inspection surface
7.8 Scan the maximum inspectable dimensional range of each inspection surface.
7.8.1 Edge signals will be excluded from the evaluation area of the C-Scan. Edge
signals are associated with index transitions from the current inspection surface
to an adjacent surface such as over an edge or onto a contour.
7.9 Evaluate all ultrasonic indications relevant to the rejection criteria in section 8.0.
7.9.1 Move the manipulator to the location of the ultrasonic indication.
7.9.2 Maximize the response of the ultrasonic indication by manipulating the various
ultrasonic axis.
7.9.3 Record any ultrasonic indication with an amplitude equal to or greater than 20
percent vertical screen height.
7.9.4 Mark on the disk surface the location of sound entry in line with the ultrasonic
indication which has an amplitude equal to or greater than the rejection criteria
defined in the corresponding NDIP.
7.9.5 Evaluate and record mean (average) Noise level
7.9.5.1 Select largest area possible not including edge signals or ultrasonic
indications.
7.9.5.2 Record the mean (average) noise level for the entire C-Scan.
7.9.5.3 Average noise level for the entire C-Scan area shall be less than or
equal to 7.5%, excluding edge effect. If average noise level is greater
than 7.5%, re-calibrate, re-normalize, and re-scan.
7.9.5.4 The maximum noise level for any given band in the C-Scan is 8.5%. If
band noise level is greater than 8.5%, re-calibrate, re-normalize, and
re-scan.
7.9.5.5 For the case when noise banding is present in the amplitude C-Scan,
select the largest area associated with the noise band. Time of Flight
(TOF) C-Scan may be used to refine the location of noise banding.

=== PAGE 16 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
13
7.9.6 Evaluate indications based on TOF rejection criteria.
7.9.7 Save all inspection results to a file and record the filename on the inspection
data sheet.
7.10 Disk cleaning
7.10.1 When scanning is complete wipe clean all surfaces and use compressed air to dry

=== PAGE 17 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
14
8.0 REJECTION CRITERIA
8.1 Any HPT disk exhibiting a rejectable ultrasonic indication(s) must be removed from
service and returned to Pratt & Whitney.
8.1.1 Rejection criteria will include analysis of time-of-flight and amplitude C-Scan data
8.1.2 Amplitude C-Scan Criteria:
8.1.2.1 Indications shall be a minimum of a three (3) pixel grouping with
adjacent pixel depths within 0.025” of one another. Groupings
smaller than 3 pixels are considered non-relevant and disregarded –
see Figure 3.
Figure 3 – examples of 3 pixel groupings
8.1.2.2 REJECTION CRITERIA: Max amplitude of three (3) pixel cluster, as
defined above, must be equal to or exceed 25% of FBH#1 (Set FBH#1
to 80%FSH, Reject at 20%FSH, Evaluation at 15%FSH)
8.1.3 Time of Flight C-Scan Criteria:
8.1.3.1 Indications shall meet the following criteria:
8.1.3.1.1 minimum of a fifteen (15) pixel grouping (reference
8.1.3.3)
8.1.3.1.2 adjacent pixels forming a group shall share edges. Do
not include pixels oriented diagonally only.
8.1.3.1.3 adjacent scan pixel depths within 0.025”
8.1.3.1.4 adjacent index pixel depths within 0.010”
8.1.3.1.5 at least three (3) adjacent scan lines
8.1.3.2 Groupings smaller than fifteen (15) pixels are considered non-
relevant and disregarded

=== PAGE 18 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
15
8.1.3.3 Reject discontinuities with at least fifteen (15) pixels, connected
along an edge and having a Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) exceeding 1.5
to 1 or greater from mean (average) of amplitude C-scan not
including C-Scan edges (section 7.7).
8.1.3.3.1 SNR refers to individual pixel amplitude divided by
mean (average) noise level, for corresponding noise
band.
8.1.3.3.2 When the average noise of the C-Scan is below
5%FSH, the TOF rejection criteria will be set to
7.5%FSH. This corresponds to evaluating a C-Scan
with a mean noise of 5%FSH.
8.1.4 Amplitude and TOF indications resulting from the interface signal encroaching
into the inspection gate are subject to the following supplemental evaluations. If
the indication fails to meet any of the prescribed conditions/persists after
corrective action, then the location is rejectable.
8.1.4.1 For a given scan line, if interface signal is widening/contracting
rather than moving, then encroachment is most-likely caused by
surface roughness. Move gate start outside of interface signal and
re-scan the location to ensure there are no other signals in the gate
that could meet the rejection criterion.
8.1.4.2 For a given scan line, if interface signal is moving in-and-out of the
gate rather than widening/contracting, then the encroachment is
most-likely caused by run-out. Adjust water path to local area and
re-scan the location to ensure there are no other signals in the gate
that could meet the rejection criterion.
8.1.4.3 For a given scan line, if interface signal is stationary within the gate,
then the encroachment is most-likely caused by a water path
deviation. Adjust transducer to intended water path and re-scan the

=== PAGE 19 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
16
location to ensure there are no other signals in the gate that could
meet the rejection criterion.
8.1.5 Amplitude and TOF indications suspected to be contributed to water
contamination/debris (“Floaters”) are subject to local re-scan to confirm
repeatability. If repeatable, indication is rejectable.
8.1.5.1 Floaters are characterized by single scan line pixel clusters.

=== PAGE 20 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
17
9.0 REPORTING
9.1 Report inspection results to Pratt & Whitney detailing the following information
9.1.1 Inspector Name, Inspection Date, Inspection System SN, Transducer SN,
Calibration Standard SN.
9.1.2 Aircraft serial number, and engine position.
9.1.3 Engine model, engine serial number, and engine total time and total cycles.
9.1.4 HPT disk part number, HPT disk serial number, HPT disk heat code, and total part
time and total part cycles since new and last inspection.
9.1.5 Inspection method, and location and amplitude of rejectable ultrasonic
indication(s):
9.1.5.1 Electronic report detailing the A-scan presentation showing the
maximum amplitude.
9.1.5.2 Electronic report detailing the position of the rejectable ultrasonic
indication(s).
9.1.6 Electronic amplitude & time of flight C-Scan data sent to Pratt & Whitney MPE-
NDE. A managed file transfer (MFT) site will be established to facilitate data
transfer.

=== PAGE 21 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
18
9.1.7 Any rejectable indication must include, refer to Appendix A:
9.1.7.1 Inspection Date
9.1.7.2 Inspector Name
9.1.7.3 Inspection System
9.1.7.4 Inspection System Serial Number
9.1.7.5 Transducer Part Number
9.1.7.6 Transducer Serial Number
9.1.7.7 Calibration Block Serial Number
9.1.7.8 Engine Serial Number
9.1.7.9 Disk Part Number
9.1.7.10 Disk Serial Number
9.1.7.11 Disk Heat Code
9.1.7.12 Time Since New (TSN)
9.1.7.13 Cycles Since New (CSN)
9.1.7.14 Inspection surface where found
9.1.7.15 Index location (inches)
9.1.7.16 Depth along sound path (inches)
9.1.7.17 Scan (circumferential) location (degrees)
9.1.7.18 Amplitude pixels: number greater than 2x1; 1x2 – yes/no
9.1.7.19 Calibration amplitude (80% FSH)
9.1.7.20 Peak indication amplitude, with DAC applied (%FSH)
9.1.7.21 TOF pixels: greater than 15 pixels over at least 3 scan lines – yes/no
9.1.7.22 TOF average Noise Level (% FSH – referencing amplitude C-Scan)
9.1.7.23 TOF Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR – referencing amplitude C-Scan)
9.1.7.23.1 Peak indication amplitude divided by Average Noise
Level

=== PAGE 22 ===
NDIP 1226 Rev F
Pratt & Whitney Proprietary Information – This page is subject to the restrictions on the cover page of this document.
19
Appendix A
Rejectable Indication Report
